<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Milk for babes in Christ: or Meditations, observations, and experiences. Divers cases of consceince resolved. The glorious priviledges of them that are Christs, with the way to know whether we are of that blessed number. Also, election before the foundation of the world asserted, and the faith of Gods elect, what it is: together with Christs compassions to sinners. / By Martin Fynch, a weak labourer in the Lords harvest, in Lincolnshire.</title>
            <author>Finch, Martin, 1628?-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 243 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 92 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85303</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867665</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119986</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240944880</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F944</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1481_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208743</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867665</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867665e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85303)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119986)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 190:E1481[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Milk for babes in Christ: or Meditations, observations, and experiences. Divers cases of consceince resolved. The glorious priviledges of them that are Christs, with the way to know whether we are of that blessed number. Also, election before the foundation of the world asserted, and the faith of Gods elect, what it is: together with Christs compassions to sinners. / By Martin Fynch, a weak labourer in the Lords harvest, in Lincolnshire.</title>
                  <author>Finch, Martin, 1628?-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 168 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Brewster, and are to be sold at his shop, at the sign of the three Bibles, at the west-end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 22".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Jesus Christ --  Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Predestination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119986:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119986:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Milk for Babes in Christ:</hi> OR MEDITATIONS, OBSERVATIONS, AND EXPERIENCES.</p>
            <p>Divers Cases of Conscience Resolved.</p>
            <p>The Glorious Priviledges of them that are Christs, with the way to know whether we are of that blessed number.</p>
            <p>ALSO, Election before the Foundation of the World asserted, and the Faith of Gods Elect, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is: Together with Christs Compassions to sinners.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Martin Fynch,</hi> a weak Labourer in the Lords Harvest, in <hi>Lincolnshire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Come all ye that fear God, and I will tell you what the Lord hath done for my soul, <bibl>
                  <hi>Psal. 66.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>All are yours, and ye are Christs, and Christ is Gods, <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 3.22, 23.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>I will have mercy upon whom I will have mercy, and I have Compassion on whom I will have Compassion; so then it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that sheweth mercy,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 9.15, 16.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Tho. Brewster,</hi> and are to be sold at his Shop, at the Sign of the three Bibles, at the West-end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119986:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119986:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thou art carnal, and a stranger to the paths of Sion, this ensuing Treatise will seem meer foolishness to thee: for the things therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, are spiritually discerned, but if thou art truly godly, I hope, what is
<pb facs="tcp:119986:3"/>here presented to thee, may be of some use through the supply of the Spirit of Jesus Christ. I do not bring forth this as Meat for strong men, but as Milk for Babes in Christ; it was Christs word to <hi>Peter, Feed my Lambs.</hi> There is a great deal of head knowledge abroad in the world, but I see not that growth in Grace among Professors, that growing as <hi>Cedars in Lebanon;</hi> indeed many spend their time about opinions and Aiëry Notions, which will not feed Christs Lambs, which will not make their souls thrive and grow in Grace; and among other means of the growth of Babes in Christ, I have observed abundance of the blessing of God upon Christians meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together to acquaint one another with their temptations, experiences, and the Fathers dealings with them. <hi>David</hi> tells us how he and other Saints, <hi>took sweet counsel together:</hi> how many Babes in Christ have found such meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, (through the presence of Christ)
<pb facs="tcp:119986:3"/>Milk and Hony to their souls! but O alas, what sad occasion have we to complain and lament, that though Christians in former times would ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture far to enjoy such opportunities, yet now we have liberty, and may speak often one to, and with another, yet now, O what deadness, backward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and neglect is there! surely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors, like the Virgins, slumber and sleep; and well were it, if with the Spouse we could say, I sleep, but my heart waketh. The Lord awaken and rouse up the spirits of Chr stians, that they may up and be doing; cert in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Saints are not so good as the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the world thought they would have been, when the Lord took off the yoak of bondage that galled their necks, and had such liberty and such a price put into their hands; the world thought and said, How will these peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple now have their meetings to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm one another, and to increase their party? but alas, we slumber, and the
<pb facs="tcp:119986:4"/>devil is sowing Tares, not onely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us, but within us, transforming him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self into an Angel of light, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swades many to neglect communion of Saints and meetings, to build up one another in their most holy Faith; and O how have we forgot that exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apostle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24, 25. Let us consider one another, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke unto love, and to good works, not forsaking the assembling of our selves together, as the manner of some is; but exhorting one another, and so much the more, as ye see the day approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: the Apostle speaketh there of the Saints meeting together, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he saith, Let us consider one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not forsaking the assembling of our selves together; now he presseth this, not to neglect these assemblings of themselves together, by how much the more we see the day approaching; what day is that? Why there is, 1. The day of death; and by how much the more we see that day approaching,
<pb facs="tcp:119986:4"/>Saints should lay hold upon all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of consolation and growth in grace. 2. There is a day and time of Apostacy, when even those that have been Professors shall give heed to seducing spirits, and the Doctrine of devils; and this seemeth to be the day here meant; for the Apostle within two or three verses speaketh of trampling under foot the Son of God; and by how much the more we see that day approaching, we should not neglect such opportunities; and doth not that day approach, nay have not our eyes already seen that day? do not we live in those times which the Scripture calls perilous times, wherein men shall be blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet this doth not bring Saints together. There is a third day, and that is called the day of the Lord, and is not that day approaching? is not he coming? do not we listen for that cry at midnight?</p>
            <p>Behold the Bridegroom cometh,
<pb facs="tcp:119986:5"/>and yet this day approaching doth not make us watchful and diligent in the ways of Christ; but what keepeth us off from such seekings after God, as formerly Christians were wont to have? why we are full, like the <hi>Laodiceans.</hi> O Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans! have we drawn our God dry? Hath not the Lord further of himself to communicate to us? O may not Christ say to us as he did to the <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> thou art poor and miserable! Want of love also among Christians is a great hinderance of their communion one with another; men are so rigid in their own principles, that if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers be not of the same opinion with them in every thing, they will not meet to pray together, nor confer together; O where is that Gospel Spirit of love! But I shall exceed the bounds of an Epistle; You have in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise something concerning Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb facs="tcp:119986:5"/>I know some will distaste it; that is, a Doctrine that all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils in Hell, and all carnal men have a spirit of antipathy, and spirit of opposition to; and I know those who in any measure bear witness to that Truth of God, shall be sure of opposition from the world; but through the Grace of Christ I have learnt not to fear the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of men, nor to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of their revilings: much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position hath been made against that Truth by Papists, Arminians, and of late by some that profess more of Christ; Yet none of them have or can shake that Truth; for it is the foundation of God that standeth sure; the Lord lead us into all Truth, and let thy kingdom O Lord Jesus come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and own thy despised truths and ways. Amen, even so come Lord Jesus.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Bellew</hi>
                  <date>the 17 of the month com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>March</hi> 1652.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So prays he who is waiting and longing for his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing,</hi> MARTIN FYNCH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:119986:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119986:6"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>MEditations, sighs, and groans.</hi> chap. 1. page 1</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Observations,</hi> c. 2. p. 12</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Experiences,</hi> c. 3. p. 19</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What conformity to the life of Christ is,</hi> c. 4. p. 27</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What our conformity to the death of Christ is,</hi> c. 5. p. 30</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What considerations may keep Saints from spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual pride,</hi> c. 6. p. 33</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How a Christian should mannage the affairs of this life,</hi> c. 7. p. 35</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>If the Lord bring some special sin to minde when we are going to Prayer, what a soul may gather from it,</hi> c. 8. p. 37</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How a Christian should carry himself under out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward losses and crosses,</hi> c. 9. p. 39</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What a poor Christian should do that is followed with temptations from day to day, and Satan often casteth in vain and lustful thoughts,</hi> c. 10. p. 42</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How Christians should carry themselves when the Providence of God casteth them among
<pb facs="tcp:119986:7"/>carnal and prophane people,</hi> c. 11. p. 45</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How a Christian should carry himself under the reproaches of the world,</hi> c. 12. p. 48</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What a Christian should do that is unequally yoaked, as if a believing Husband have an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing Wife, or a believing Wife have an unbelieving Husband,</hi> c. 13. p. 50</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How a Christians thoughts should be exercised about death,</hi> c. 14. p. 53</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How Christians should carry it towards their Brethren, when their Brethren are overtaken with a fault,</hi> c. 15. p. 55</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whether a Believer ought to keep the first day of the week holy and wholly unto the Lord, as a Gospel Sabboth,</hi> c. 16. p. 58</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What Christians should do in time of National troubles, wars, and uproars,</hi> c. 17. p. 60</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How Believers should mourn for sin,</hi> c. 18. p. 63</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How a soul may know whether his assurance be right or not,</hi> c. 19. p. 65</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The cause and cure of doubtings,</hi> c. 20. p. 70</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What Christians should do when they finde not that inlargement in prayer as formerly,</hi> c. 21. p. 75</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Advice to poor Christians that complain of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that they know no more of Christ,</hi> c. 22. p. 77</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:119986:7"/>
               <head>PART. II.</head>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>Text 1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29.</head>
                     <item>Doct. <hi>That all divine Priviledges, Heaven and Happiness, belong to them that are Christs, and to them onely: for the opening of which point is shewn,</hi> 1. <hi>What it is to be Christs, in seven particulars,</hi> p. 84</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Why all divine Priviledges belong to them that are Christs, and to them onely,</hi> p. 88</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>What those glorious Priviledges are that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to them that are Christs, in eleven particulars,</hi> p. 92</item>
                     <item>4 <hi>How we may know whether we are Christs, or no, in ten particulars,</hi> p. 106</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lastly, the Application,</hi> p. 116</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>Text 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48.</head>
                     <item>Doct. 1. <hi>That the God of all Grace hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ordained a certain number of poor sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to eternal life and glory; for the opening of which is shewn,</hi> 1. <hi>That this ordaining was from all eternity,</hi> p. 122</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Not of Faith and Works foreseen, but of meer Grace,</hi> p. 124</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>That Jesus Christ is ordained to be the Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the Elect,</hi> p. 125</item>
                     <item>4 <hi>That nothing can be laid to the charge of Gods Elect,</hi> p. 126</item>
                     <item>5 <hi>That its impossible they should be deceived,</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>6 <hi>That those who were ordained to eternal life,
<pb facs="tcp:119986:8"/>were ordained also to believe on Christ,</hi> p, 128</item>
                     <item>7 <hi>All things work for their good,</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>8 <hi>They cannot fall from Grace,</hi> p. 129</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Objections answered, and six Ʋses made of the point,</hi> p. 131</item>
                     <item>Doct. 2. <hi>That though many despise and reject Christ, yet those whom the Lord hath ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to eternal life, shall certainly believe on Christ; where is shown,</hi> 1. <hi>What the Faith of Gods Elect is,</hi> p. 138</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>The degrees of Faith given to the Elect,</hi> p. 142</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>With several other things concerning Faith in Christ, and Ʋses of the point,</hi> p. 144</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Christs Compassions to sinners, on</hi> Luke 10.33, 34<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> p. 154</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119986:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Occasional Meditations, Sighs, and Groans.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been the practise of the Saints all along, to spend much time in Meditation of God, and the good wayes and things of God. <hi>Isaac</hi> went into the fields to meditate; <hi>David</hi> loved to have his heart inditing a good matter concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King of Saints, <hi>Psal.</hi> 45. and sometimes when we cannot find our beloved, the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, in praying, hearing, conferring, yet we find him in Meditation; and when we are walking to meditate, he comes and walks with us, taketh us by the hand, and leadeth us, yea he kisseth us with the kisses of his mouth, whose love is better then wine; and when we are in meditation, how sweet are the thoughts of God to us? yea, every thing a Christian seeth, affordeth matter
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119986:9"/>of spiritual meditation and use to him; when he walks, to think of walking with God; when he eateth, to meditate of Christ the bread of Life; when he standeth, to meditate of stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Grace; when he seeth the love of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it putteth him in mind of the love and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der compassions of our heavenly Father: and thus by Meditation do the Saints enjoy much communion with God: now whiles Christians are thus exercised in meditation, there pass sighs and groans from their souls, with spiritual eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations and desires, of which we shall give a taste in the following particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meditation</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>MEditating upon <hi>John</hi> 13.12. where the Lord Jesus saith to his Disciples, <hi>Know ye what I have done unto you?</hi> from that passage the Lord discovered this, That the Saints should so diligently mind the dealings of God towards them every day, that if the Lord should ask a Saint at night, know ye what I have done unto you this day? know ye what I have been doing in your souls? that then we may be able to say, yea Lord, we in some measure know thou hast been humbling of us by such a providence, or thou hast been imbittering the world to me this day, or thou hast been letting me see my own nothingness and unworthiness, or thou hast been quickening, comforting, strengthening me; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creasing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119986:9"/>my Faith, or arming me against the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of the world: But O Lord, what strangers are we to our own hearts, and to the work thou art about in our souls?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 2. Its better to marry a wife, then to burn in lust; and its better to marry to Christ, then to burn in hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 3. O my dear Saviour, when I come to be where thou art, to behold thy glory, I think to magnifie thee, and to sing praises to thee for that sweet communion I have with thee, and kisses of thy mouth that I have had in this vale of tears; and therefore I remember thy love more then wine: I remember how at such times, in such places, and in such conditions thy ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners over me have been love; and yet O my dear Saviour! after all that communion I have had with thee in this vale of tears, I shall say thou hast kept the good wine until now: and O will not that fulness of joy swallow up the thoughts of my small enjoyments of thee here below! O bring me to those glorious and everlasting embracements!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 4. Lord, how doth my soul cry to thee? my groaning is not hid from thee; O satisfie me early with thy mercy; all the riches, honours, and pleasures of the world will not satisfie my soul; I find all those things to be but as Brooks that fail in Summer; O satisfie me with thy tender mercies and love; thy loving kindness
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119986:10"/>will satisfie my soul for ever, and nothing else; make no long tarrying O my God, but satisfie my longing soul early with the light of thy countenance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 5. Death is the King of Terrors: Lord, be pleased to give me such a full assurance of thy love, that when sickness comes, I may not fear that the time of my appointed change is come, but that I may hope that the time of my departure is at hand, and desire to be dissolved, to be with Christ; yea O my God, let the assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of thy love be so strong, that when I come to walk through the valley of the shadow of death, that I may fear no evil.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 6. Sin is not only an enemy unto par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, but to peace; and though a great sin can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take away a Believers great pardon, yet sometimes a little sin takes away his little peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 7. Dear Saviour, <hi>Thou hast prayed for thine, that they may be where thou art, to behold thy glory,</hi> John 17. O I see but little that thou hast in this world; for I see thee despised and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected of men, which maketh me exceedingly long to see that glory which thou hast at the right hand of the Majesty on high.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 8. I had rather God should do any thing without me, as an instrument, then that I should do any thing without him. Its better that God should act without me, then that I should act vvithout him: O my God, that in all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119986:10"/>my undertakings for thee, that I may have thy presence with me!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 9. Lord, I would not live without thee, but by thee; and not only by thee, but with thee, who art the fountain of my life; neither doth my soul desire only to live by thee, and with thee, but also to live for thee, and to thee for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 10. Lord, That I may not be sad or merry according as Creature-comforts are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent or absent, but according as my soul enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth or not enjoyeth communion with thee: That my soul may never be sad and troubled, but when thou hidest thy face; neither to rejoyce in any thing besides thy self; that the world may be nothing to me, and that thou maist be all in all for comfort and consolation to my soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 11. The Ordinances are helpers of our joy; so are the Ministers of Christ; Lord, help me to rejoyce in thee, in them, and by them, in thee who art the gladness of my heart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 12. Concerning Witches: That some Witches may be saved, and the league between them and the Devil broken; besides that instance of <hi>Mannsseh,</hi> two Scriptures compared together hold forth as much: 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.23. and <hi>Psal.</hi> 68.18. The one saith Rebellion is as Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, that is to say, as abominable to God, and as provoking of the eyes of his glory; and the other Scripture in the <hi>Psalms</hi> saith, I hat Jesus
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119986:11"/>Christ hath received gifts for men, yea, for the Rebellious, that the Lord God might dwell amongst them, that they may be habitations of God through the Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 13. Lord, thou hast promised thou wilt not leave thine, nor forsake them <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. thou wilt not leave them in their sins, nor for their sins, nor to their sins; and Lord, should I leave thee in my sufferings, or for my tribulations for thy sake? O whither should I go! thou only hast the words of eternal life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 14. Its a sad thing when men are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, and other men know the cause better then themselves: Lord, shew me thy mind in all thy dealings with me, and let it be good for me that I am afflicted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 15. I am much refresht in meditating of the Saints glorious Resurrection unto eternal life; Lord, that I may have a part in the first Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection, the Lord Jesus, and know the power of his Resurrection! so when I awake, I shall be satisfied with thy likeness.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 16. I do not wonder to see a Saint sometimes sad; the heart knoweth his own bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terness; and it is no wonder to see a Saint some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times rejoycing with joy unspeakable and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; when Christ smiles and kisses, who can but rejoyce? when Christ cometh to a droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing soul, and saith to it, as <hi>Joseph</hi> said to him that was in prison, why lookest thou so sadly to day?
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119986:11"/>be of good chear, I am thy salvation; then the soul must needs be exceeding glad: O my God, help me over al my difficulties temptations cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, fears, doubtings, and let all my sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row be for sin, and all my joy be in Christ.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 17. O the infinite love of the Father, in choosing and setting his love upon the greatest of sinners! O the bleeding wounds of Christ, who hath been wounded for our transgressions! O that sweet Spirit of Grace, that convinceth of sin, and of righteousness, and which taketh of the Father, and of Christ, and sheweth them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 18. Lord thou dost not look at our parts, but at our hearts: O give me that truth in the inwards parts; let my heart be upright be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, O my God, and purge my heart of all hypocrisie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 19. Lord, I see abundance of good in thy holiness, love, wisdom, compassion, long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suffering; but Lord, if thou lookest upon me in my self, thou wilt see abundance of evil in me, unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, pride, ignorance, deadness, unserviceableness; for in me, that is, in my flesh dwelleth no good thing: but O my God, let me know that I am beloved in thy Beloved, and that the robes of his righteousness covereth all my sins, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents me to thee without spot or wrinkle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 20. Lord, I have had some sweet commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with thee in time past, some I enjoy at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119986:12"/>O I long for that fulness of joy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion to come; O come Lord Jesus, come quickly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 21. Why should I fear poverty? the Earth is the Lords, and the fulness thereof: what should I regard the having of a bad name, and the being reproacht by the world, if I have the white stone, and the new name?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 22. Lord, whilst it is day, help me to be doing the work for which thou sentest me into the world; the night is coming, wherein no man can work; the night of sickness, the night of old age, and the night of age; Lord, that thou hadst never cause to say to me, why stand you idle?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 23. Lord, thou lookest upon the proud afar off; O keep me humble: if thou bestowest gifts and graces upon me, let me be as humble as if I had none: if I have riches, let me be as hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as if I had none: if I have honour from men, keep me as humble as if I had none: in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions hide pride from my heart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 24. The graves are ready for me, O that I were ready for the graves; and O that I may wait not only when I come to be sick, or come to be old, but wait all the days of my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time, untill my change shall come.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 25. This may be one reason why, though the Apostles prayed so much, yet none of their prayers are set down in the Scripture,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119986:12"/>because we should not use set formes of Prayer, but that we should pray by that same spirit by which they prayed, which spirit of grace and supplication maketh intercession for us accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 26. Jesus Christ was a great while with his Disciples before he gave them the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; me thinks it should hold forth thus much unto us, that we should know them well with whom we joyn in that Ordinance. O when shall we have pure Ordinances, and a difference put between the precious and the vile!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 27. Meditating upon the long lives of the Saints under the Old-Testament, and how short the lives of the Saints are now; and thinking of the reason; I conceived, because then the way of salvation was not so well known; and besides, to speak after the manner of men, the Lord Jesus having now dyed and perfected for ever them that are Sanctified, he longs now to see all his children in Heaven.</p>
               <p n="28">28. <hi>Meditation upon the choice of a Wife.</hi> We should not take her into such a neer and deer relation to be a wife to us, whom the Lord Jesus hath not taken into that neer and deer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to be a spouse unto him; we should not chose them to lie in our bosoms, who have not lien in the bosome of our dear Saviour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 29. Creatures like leaves pluckt off do die and wither: But our God the same abides for ever.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:119986:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 30, Lord, as thou hast given me senses suited for the use of my body: So Lord give me spiritual senses suited for a spiritual heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly soul.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A spiritual taste whereby I may taste and see how good the Lord is, <hi>Psal.</hi> 34.8. and may from an experimental taste say, thy love is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then Wine. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. O my God, give me a spiritual hearing; let me hear the voice behind me saying, This is the way, walk in it: let me have an ear to hear thy voice who speakest peace unto thy people.</p>
               <p n="3">3. O that I may have a spiritual sight, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may have a view of Christ the fairest of ten thousand, and that from that sight of Christ to be able to say his countenance is most sweet, yea he is altogether lovely.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A spiritual smelling; whereby I may finde sweetness in that Rose of <hi>Sharon,</hi> the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, whose Garments smell of Myrrh.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A spiritual feeling; O let me never be of those who are past feeling; O but let me feel the love of Christ chearing, warming, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting me at the heart; let me spiritually han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the Word of life, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1, 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 31. Men prize scarce commodities: the Saints are a scarce commodity, there is but few of them, and yet these few are not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; yet my soul saith, They are the excellent on the earth, in whom is all my delight; they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119986:13"/>are more excellent then their neighbours, though their neighbours be rich, and they poor, though their neighbours be honoured, and they despised.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 32. Lord, I bless thee that ever I knew thee and thy ways, and that I have bid farewel to all the pleasures of sin that are but for a sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; O let me have so much communion with thee, that I may stand and make my boast in God, and oppose the enjoyments my soul hath in Christ, to all those pleasures of sin that are but for a season.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 33. When I am in communion with God, and meet with a Christian that at the same time is so, O what heavenly discourse! O how do our hearts burn within us whilst we speak of our beloved Jesus!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:119986:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Containing Observations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. I Observe men to be full of extreams.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>First as to Prayer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Some will not pray but when they have a special motion of the spirit to pray; and if they have not such a special motion in a week or a month, or yeer, they will neglect the seeking of God all that while, whereas the Holy Ghost saith we should pray always, continually, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.19. And <hi>David</hi> prayed seven times a day; surely neglect of Prayer will not fit for Prayer; and I have observed great deadness, coldness, and lukewarmness to grow upon such professors; this is one extream.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Others observe some set times for Prayer, it may be morning and evening, and will never seek the face of God but then; though at other times they have motions to pray, or finde some temptations to a sin very strong, yet they will not go to seek the face of God for strength against the temptation; or though they fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to some great sin, yet they will not go and lie down in their shame before the Lord. Its said they shall go speedily to the Lord: It may be thy heart will not be so melted and broken before
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119986:14"/>the Lord at an evening duty for a sin commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted about noon, as if thou hadst gone presently to God and bewailed the baseness of thy heart, and poured out thy soul before him — this is another extream.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Secondly, As to places of hearing and meeting.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Some come to the publique places, as pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces more holy then other places, and will not hear or meet elsewhere; but call those places the houses of God; and those people, though they say they love the house of God so much, yet indeed they love not the true houses of God which is the Saints, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17. By those Scriptures we may see that the Saints are the houses of God; now these people come not to hear in these publike places as convenient places for meeting, as where there is room e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and convenient seats, but as I said before, they come to them as to places more holy then others; here's one extream.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Others because those places have been used to superstition, will not hear in them at all, as if Christ had not said, wheresoever two or three are met together in my name, I will be in the midst of them, wheresoeverin publike or private house, field, anywhere: and we shall finde that <hi>Paul</hi> preacht in <hi>Mars</hi>-hill, a place where there was abundance of superstition acted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Thirdly, As to Baptism.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Some they are so much upon Baptism
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119986:15"/>with water, that they never minde the Baptism with the Holy Ghost and with fire, which is the chiefe Baptism.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Others despise Baptism with water, saying that the Baptism with the spirit is the Baptism: Irs true, it's the most excellent Baptism; but doth Baptism with water an Ordinance of Christ hinder the Baptism of the spirit?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Fourthly, As to Preachers.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Some will hear none but such as have been at the Vniversities, though they be never so gifted and experienced. Although I conceive that an Vniversity is a very good place to bring up young men in; yet where do we finde in the Scripture that none but such as have been at Vniversities must Preach the Gospel? this is one extream.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. I observe others are so prejudiced against those who by Gods providence have been brought up in the Vniversities, that though they be never so gifted, experienc't in the ways of Christ, never such able Ministers of the New-Testament, not of the letter but of the spirit, yet they are slighted: these things ought not so to be. As Christ called <hi>Peter</hi> and others that were fishermen, to bear his name and publish the glad tidings of the Gospel, so he called <hi>Paul</hi> who was a great scholler, and brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel.</hi> Oh when shall we have the faith of our Lord Jesus without respect of persons?</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119986:15"/>II. I observe many men to be high in Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and opinions, and speak fluently to men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, but when they come to speak to God in prayer, they are very flat and dead, and formal.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. I observe that Sathan is very busie to break off the Saints communion and love in the spirit; and sometimes the spirits of Christians clash, and there is not that harmony and sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in their spirits one to another; but yet at other times the same Christians close sweetly, and have much heavenly discourse.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. I observe that those professors that spend their time so much about opinions, have but little experience in the ways of Christ, and are very ignorant of regeneration and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God The Lord make us wise to salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we may minde the one thing necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; more time will come when that question will be asked, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.) where are the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputers of the world, that made it their business to dispute some controversies, and to hold an Argument? and I have too much ground to think that many of them read the Scriptures chiefly to maintain an opinion; which is very sad.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. I observe many that take the Law for the Gospel, and the Gospel for the Law; it will be of much use to a Christian to distinguish aright between the Law and Gospel.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119986:16"/>VI. I observe that some men in discourse are glad they can close, others are glad they cannot close; O what spirits are we of!</p>
                  <p n="7">VII. I see the fairest day hath some clouds; and if godly men grow great in the world, they have some eminent crosses, that they may see here is not their rest, and their happiness. I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve a kinde of equality in mens conditions, as to the things of this world; some have riches, and want health; some way or other the sweets of this world are mixt with bitters; there is no solid standing comfort out of Christ, who is a Believers all in all.</p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. I observe, the more loose professors are themselves, the more censorious and uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable they are to others.</p>
                  <p n="9">IX. I observe your blunt, plain-dealing, free, open-hearted Christians do abundance of good; the Lord take away that sinful silence and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty that is in many Christians, and teach us how to speak, and when to speak by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, advice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">X. One remarkable thing I observed in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course with one that was in prison for a Witch, and confessed she was one; it arose upon this question; I askt her whether in the place where she had lived there was none that the world cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Puritans, Roundheads, or Independents? she told me there was. I asked her whether she never had a minde to do them mischief? she told
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119986:16"/>me she had a minde oftentimes, but could not, especially to one professor, her neer neighbour, he having some way given her distaste, which she resolved to revenge when her Imps came to her; as she said, they came every twenty four hours; it was in the evening she sent them to kill three fat Swine he had in a place neer to his house; so they went, and the man was at Prayer in his family, and they went back and told the Witch that man was calling upon God, and they could do no harm to him or any thing that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to him; the witch was very sorry she could not have her will upon him: she sent her Imps another time, and his son was reading the Scriptures; they returned and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d the witch, that man and his house served the Lord, and they could do him no harm if she sent them never so often. This I think is worth the taking notice of by all the people of God, that they may live by Faith, and depend upon him who is able to keep them, so that the evil one touch them not, as <hi>Numb</hi> 23.27. <hi>There is no inchantment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Jacob, neither is there any divination a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain Israel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">XI. This day being the 28 of <hi>October,</hi> 1652. I had a remarkable Providence before my eyes, to let me see how uncertain our lives are in this world; the thing was this, one digging stones in a pit belonging to the Town where I live, and undermining the earth much, the top of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119986:17"/>the pit fell, which was about twenty load of earth, and slew him that he never spoak. <hi>Lord, teach me so to number my days, that I may apply my heart unto wisdom;</hi> and let even this Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence dead my heart to the world, and to all the enjoyments here below, which are so soon taken from us, or we from them.</p>
                  <p n="12">XII. Sometimes I think there is abundance of God in some men; but when I come into their company, worldly discourse or sinful silence hindereth our communion in the Spirit.</p>
                  <p n="13">XIII. I observe that as God speaketh to us by some men; so the devil speaketh to us by others, as the devil spake to <hi>Adam</hi> by <hi>Eve.</hi> O that we may know when the Lord speaketh, and when 'tis Sathan that speaketh.</p>
                  <p n="14">XIV. I observe too many that take more care, and have more desire to get into Christ, then that Christ should get into them; they take more care to get into the kingdom of God, then that the kingdom of God should get into them.</p>
                  <p n="15">XV. I observe some that pretend to much brokenness of heart, and sorrow for sin, and yet speak against the preaching of Christ and Free-grace: Surely were their hearts indeed broken, were they indeed heavy-laden, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of Christ, and Free-grace would be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to them, would be sweeter to them then hony and the hony-comb.</p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119986:17"/>XVI. I observe that loose professors cannot bear fast duties.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Experiences.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Experience.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>O How true in my own soul do I finde that of the Apostle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. for the Flesh lusteth against the Spirit, and the Spirit against the Flesh, so that ye cannot do the things which ye would! when the Spirit and Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate part in me would pray, the Flesh rebelleth against it, and it would not; and when I would meditate, the flesh rebelleth and would not; and when the Spirit would submit to all the dealings of God, and say, <hi>Not my will, but thy will be done,</hi> the flesh would not: and when I would commune with my own heart upon my bed, and make diligent search, the flesh rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and would not; and so on the contrary, the Spirit and regenerate part opposeth the flesh: and when the flesh would delight it self in the pleasures of sin that are but for a season, the spirit opposeth the flesh, and it would not; when the flesh would delight it self in vanity,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119986:18"/>the spirit would not, but crieth, and groans, and sighs, saying, Lord, turn away mine eys from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding vanity; thus is there a strugling and striving in my soul, between the flesh and the Spirit; and because the flesh doth so oppose the spirit, I cannot do the good which I would, as I would do it; I cannot pray as I would, nor hear as I would, nor meditate of the things of God as I would. Lord, do thou deliver me from this Law of my members, and let me however delight in thee and thy ways, after the inward man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 2. A Saint when he is overtaken with a sin, and cometh to see his backslidings, he hateth that sin more then ever; its the object of his soul, and maketh him cry out, O this pride! O these vain thoughts, how abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are they to my soul! But the ungodly are not so: but the more they commit a sin, the more they love it, and delight in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 3. Sometimes after the commission of a sin we cannot pray; the heart is even stupified, and hath contracted so much hardness, that the soul maketh too much delay before he goeth to the Lord to take away all his iniquities, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him graciously.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 4. Sometime the God of all Grace hideth his face from his people a good while, upon the commission of a sin; and sometime it may be the same day that it hath fallen into
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119986:18"/>some great sin, to let us see his love is free, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth us joy unspeakable and glorious, which love of God will melt the heart into tears, and make the poor soul say, Lord, did I look to have sweet communion with thee at this time, seeing I have so lately dishonoured thee, and sinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee! I might rather have expected that thou shouldst have writ bitter things against me, and caused me to go mourning all my days without the light of thy countenance. O thy Grace and love, and pity to my soul!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 5. Sometimes a poor soul seeing how God hath blotted out his transgressions, and will remember his sins no more, but if his sins should be sought for, they cannot be found, the soul is filled with such Gospel-sorrow for his sinning against the God of love, that whether it be joy or sorrow he can scarce tell; for he at the same time mourns for his own vilenss, and and rejoyceth in the free mercy and love of God unto him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 6. I finde no discontent, but a sweet submission to God in my heart, whatsoever condition I am in, but when I think of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, delights, and advancement in the world. Lord, let me never think of being rich in the world; that Lord, if it be thy will I may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be poor; let me never think of being high and great, that so I may be content to be low and mean; let me never think of being
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119986:19"/>honoured and esteemed, that so I may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be despised and counted the off scour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper</hi> 7. If Christians have joyned together in the commission of a sin, or have had worldly joy together, they have the harder thoughts one of another, and have not afterwards such sweet communion in the ways of God; which should make Christians very watchful in their conversations one towards another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 8. We are apt to mistake our way af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the commission of a sin; either we so aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate it that we even despair, and think God will not pardon it, or else we lessen it, so as we go not to God with that brokenness of heart and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sorrow, putting our mouths in the dust, which we should do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 9. I find formality to be a great hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance to communion with Christ, and growth in grace, and that I may lose Christ upon my knees: so that by a formal and remiss perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of duties, my heart is in a worse frame then before. Lord, keep me from formality and deadness in thy ways, but quicken me according to thy word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 10. I finde that the greatest prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I usually have for duties and Ordinances, is that my soul thirsteth and breaths after com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God. Lord, maintain this frame of spirit, and never send my thirsty soul empty away from thy presence.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:119986:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 11. Somtimes I am much inlarged to speak of the things of God, when the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God casteth me among natural peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but most of general truths; it will do them good, or me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 12. <hi>August</hi> 19. 1650. That day a poor soul having been often tempted and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about the time of his conversion, the Lord was pleased to help him to believe and act faith upon the Lord Jesus, as if he had never believed before; the Spirit of Christ convinc'd him of sin, and of righteousness, and the soul closed with Christ by faith, as if he had never done it before; and the Lord help their souls that are troubled about the time of their conversion to set upon the work afresh.</p>
               <p>The same day the poor soul resolved from that time through the strength of Christ to live as one in Christ, as one that was called out of darkness into marveilous light.</p>
               <p>The Lord was pleased to give that poor soul much Gospel sorrow and brokenness of heart, as also joy and peace in believing, and gave in that good word to his soul, I am thy Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Then that soul chose afresh, rather to suffer affliction with the people of God, then to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the pleasures of sin for a season.</p>
               <p>Then the poor soul said, Return unto thy rest, O my soul; for the Lord hath dealt bountifully
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119986:20"/>with me; he hath blotted out as a thick cloud my transgressions, and remembers my sins no more; yea he hath caused his face to shine upon me.</p>
               <p>O then how that poor soul did abhor himself in dust and ashes! How did he see an all love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness and excellency in the Lord Jesus.</p>
               <p>Then that poor soul would not have changed his condition for ten thousand worlds; he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred his ways, and was ashamed when he saw the Lord was pacified for all he had done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him.</p>
               <p>That day the soul desired of the Lord if it were his will, that having had that day such an assurance of his everlasting love, that he might never doubt more and question his love, but might to his dying day have the joy of his salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and be established with his free spirit.</p>
               <p>The same day that poor soul desired the Lord to keep him always in an humble melting frame, that he might walk humbly with that God that had done such great things for his soul.</p>
               <p>The same day the soul desired this of God, that if the Lord bad no intent to make any use of him for his glory, that he might even that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day be dissolved to be with Christ.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 13. Some time after, the same poor soul was heavy laden with sin, and went mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a while without the Sun, until God was pleased to speak peace to him by that promise, <hi>Hos.</hi> 14 4. <hi>I will heal thy back-slidings, I will love thee freely.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:119986:20"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 14. If a soul can submit freely to the will of God in the worst condition, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est affliction, he shall find more comfort in it, then if he were in the best condition he desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth; a poor Christian that hath sweet content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in poverty, sickness, hath more true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in that condition, then if he were rich and had health.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 15. I finde its a sweet thing when the spirit of Christ stirreth in the soul, as soon as lust stirreth, and corruption stirreth: for then the soul is easily taken off from satisfying the lust, and closeth with the breathings and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 16. When a hint or sweet discovery is first given in, its much more sweet then when its remembred afterwards, or written down.</p>
               <p>A truth is far sweeter in the heart, then in the head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 17. If men had the bitterness of sin go before the sweetness of it, their akes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, sense of guilt, black fears, they would not sin so much as they do; men will finde first or last sin to be a root of bitterness; how should we pray with <hi>David!</hi> Lord, lead me in the way everlasting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 18. <hi>June</hi> 13. 1652. That day the Lord was pleased to give a weak Christian strong consolation from <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Blessed are they which hunger and thirst after righteousness,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119986:21"/>for they shall be filled;</hi> the spirit of Christ did bear witness that the poor heart did sincerely hunger and thirst after righteousnes, by which is meant the Lord Jesus, the Lord our righte ous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; and the Lord gave the poor soul assurance, that though he was then poor in spirit, and saw but little of Christ in him, yet he should be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and receive of Christs fulness, and grace for grace; and at that time the soul had experience of this, that where the spirit of Christ doth bear witness to the truth of grace in the soul, it doth at that time increase grace in the soul; as when the spirit doth bear witness to the soul that it hath true love to Christ, it doth at that time increase the souls love to Christ, that the soul loveth Christ more then before; and so for joy in Christ, and so for hungering and thirsting after Christ, when the spirit doth wieness to a soul that it hath a true hunger and thirst after Christ, at that time it doth increase the souls hunger and thirst after Christ, as that soul found that day that he hungred and thirsted after Christ more then ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exper.</hi> 19. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 23. 1652. A poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture being sick and weak, and waiting for the time of his appointed change, the Lord gave in these words, <hi>Thou shalt not die but live, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the wondrous works of the Lord;</hi> O said the poor creature, Bless the Lord O my soul, and forget not all his benefits who forgiveth all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119986:21"/>thine iniquities, and healeth all thy diseases, who redeemeth thy life from destruction, who crowneth thee with loving kindness, and tender mercies; the poor creature recovered, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sireth the remainder of his few and evil days to live unto God, and not to himself.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>What our conformity to the life of Christ is.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT should be the desire of every Disciple of Christ to be like his Master; and that Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an hath attained to a high pitch of grace,
<note place="margin">Verus Christi est amator qui etiam Christi est imitator.</note> that is Christ-like in all his ways. Now being conformable to the life of Christ, or our being Christ-like, lieth in these things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It was Christs meat and drink to do the will of the Father, <hi>Joh</hi> 4.34. So the more we delight to do the will of God, and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments are not grievous to us, the more Christ-like we are.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Lord Jesus was meek and lowly in heart, <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.9. Christ was so humble and lowly, that he rode into that famous City of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119986:22"/>
                  <hi>Jerusalem</hi> upon an Asse; so humble to wash his Disciples feet, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13. And therefore <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. Christ bids us learn of him; for saith he, I am meek and lowly in heart; now the more humble, meek, and lowly in heart we are, the more conformable we are to the life of our dear Saviour; but O how unlike are we to Christ!</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Lord Jesus was patient in all the scorns and reproaches he met withal from the world, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.23. When he was reviled, he reviled not again; now the more patient we are in tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and reproaches, the more like to Christ.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Lord Jesus was much in Prayer, and therefore often went into the mountains for that end; and the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> saith <hi>cap.</hi> 5.7. that in the days of his flesh he offered up supplications with strong crying and tears to him that was able to deliver him. So the more we by the same spirit of grace and suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation are crying to the father of Spirits for those things we stand in need of, the more like to the Captain of our Salvation. O that we might walk as he walked!</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Lord Jesus was very full of compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; when he saw objects of pity, as the blind, the lame, the leprous, he had compassion on them; and the more pittiful and compassionate we are to men, the more like to our dear Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119986:22"/>who knoweth how to have compassion on the ignorant, and of them that are out of the way.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Lord Jesus was not taken with all the glory of this world, when the devil as we have it in the fourth of <hi>Matthew,</hi> took him up to a high pinacle, and shewed him all the kingdoms of the world; so the more our hearts are deaded to the world, and we see them to be all but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, the more like to our dear Saviour.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Our Lord Jesus was despised, reviled, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> was jeered, mocked, scorned, hated; and the more we are jeered, despised, mocked, reviled, hated, and have evil spoken of us for righteousness sake, the more like we are to our dear Saviour, when as he was, so are we in this present world, when as he was hated, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, despised, reviled, so are we in and from the world.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The Lord Jesus was much in denying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, although he was the heir of all things, and might have commanded all the enjoyments of the world, yet he denyed himself, and had not in this world whereon to lay his head. O the wonderful self-denyal of Christ! and the more we deny our selves and take up our cross, the more we follow Christs example.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119986:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>What our conformity to the death of Christ is.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Scripture speaketh more of Christs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a patern and example to us in his life, then in his death; yet in both he is exemplary to the Saints; hence the Apostle speaks of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conformable to his death, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10. That I may know him, saith he, and the power of his Resurrection, and the fellowship of his suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, being made conformable to his death; not as though the Lord Jesus was onely a pattern and example in his death, as some conceive, and slight the merit of his death, and that redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption we have in his blood, even the forgiveness of sins, according to the riches of his grace; the main end of his death, was to purge away our sins by the sacrifice of himself, and to bring us unto God; therefore he was made sin and a curse for us, that we might be made the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness of God in him; and this being well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered, there is no danger, but abundance of use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness in making the death of Christ a patern and exemplary unto Believers. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119986:23"/>1 <hi>Pet,</hi> 3.18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. Now I shall not speak of a Notional, but Spiritual and Practical conformity to the death of our dear Saviour.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Then the Lord Jesus in the business of his death was submitted to the will of the Father, thoug as a man he lawfully might desire the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of his life; yet in that which he might thus lawfully desire, he was wholly sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the fathers will, saying, <hi>Father, not my will, but thy will be done,</hi> Matth. 26.39. So the more we are submitted to the will of God, the more willing we are to be at his dispose, and can truly say, Lord, here I am, do what thou wilt with me; the more conformable we are to the Lord Jesus in the business of his death, when in all conditions, afflictions, losses, crosses, we can say, not as I will, but as thou wilt; now this a hard lesson, as we shall finde; but if we will write after Christs copy, and follow his example, we must do thus.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Lord Jesus in his death overcame him that had the power of death, which is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. Now our overcoming the Prince of darkness, is conformity to his death; now 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.13. the Apostle saith that the young men in Christ had overcome the wicked one, that is the devil; now indeed if Christ in his death had not overcome Sathan, we could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver overcome him; but when the Captain of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119986:24"/>our Salvation hath once overcome him, its the easier for us to do it, as to overcome one that is already overcome is easie; this is the second.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Christ in his death was so patient, that the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> saith, <hi>He was led like a lamb to the slaughter, and as a sheep before the shearers is dumb, so he opened not his mouth,</hi> Isa. 53.7. So the more patient we are in all sufferings, reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, fiery trials, the more conformable to Christs death.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Our Lord Jesus died unto sin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.10. The Lord Jesus, though he himself was without sin, yet those for whom he died were sinners, ungodly; now the Lord Jesus undertaking for them, and having all their sins laid upon him, because these were (<hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14.) to be holy, a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar people, he in their stead died unto sin; so now when our old man is crucified, the flesh with its affections and lusts, and we to walk in newness of life, the body of sin destroyed, that henceforth we serve not sin, as you shall see the Apostle maketh Christ a pattern to us in his dying unto sin; for having spoken of Christ dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto sin, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. in the 11 <hi>ver.</hi> saith he, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise reckon ye also your selves to be dead in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed unto sin; but alive unto God through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ our Lord; and saith he, let not sin reign in your mortal bodies; so that this is part of our conformity to the death of Christ, when as he dyed unto sin, we also are dead to sin, and live no longer therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119986:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>What considerations may work upon Christians to cause them to walk humbly with God, and keep them from spiritual pride.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. LEt a poor Saint consider that God might have glorified himself in his destruction, and never have called him into the fellowship of his son Jesus Christ.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Remember, that though now you walk with God, and live godly in Christ Jesus, yet ye were sometimes foolish, disobedient, serving divers lusts, walkt in the vanity of your mindes, and had your conversations according to the course of this world, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Consider who maketh us to differ, and that we have nothing but what we have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and if we have received it, why are we puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed up as if we had not received it? (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7.) nothing but free-grace hath made a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between us and the prophanest creatures in the world.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Consider what unprofitable servants we have been to Christ since conversion, of what
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119986:25"/>little use we have been for God in the world, and how barren and unfruitful we have been in the knowledge of Jesus; well may such walk humbly with God.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Consider that God is not beholding to us for any thing we do for him; for its in his strength we do it, and without him we can do nothing.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To keep us from spiritual pride, let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider and think often of the great sins we have fallen into since conversion; and then we shall see cause enough to lie low before our God.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Continually remember how displeasing spiritual pride is to God; pride is thought to be the condemnation of the Angels that kept not their first estate, who are now so misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; being reserved in chains of darkness to the blackness of the great day; the Lord, as it is written, looketh upon the proud afar off, he will not come neer them to have intimacy and communion with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119986:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>How a Christian should carry him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in civil affairs, in manna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the affairs of this life.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>EVery Christian hath to do more or less in civil affairs; as working, buying, selling; how then should he carry himself in such affairs?</p>
               <p n="1">1. A Christian must in all have his convers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without covetousness, and be content with the things that he hath. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Christian must mannage his affairs of this life without a distracting care; as not to have a distracting care what he should eat, what he should drink, what will be the issue of such a business.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Christian is to have a care that no worldly employment hinder him from walking with God, and having communion with God; its a sad thing when a Christian shall sit down, &amp; have cause to say, O how I am cumbred about many things! I have such a croud of outward business that I do not walk with my God as I was wont, I do not enjoy so much communion with my God as I was wont.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In all thy affairs beware of sin; O keep
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119986:26"/>from all the pollutions of the world, pride, oppression, deceit.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If that through the blessing of God upon thy lawful care and pains about the things of this life, thy riches increase, have a care of set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thy heart upon them.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Often remembet that the Lord saith, Give me thy heart, that none of the things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low may have our hearts and affections, but the Lord onely.</p>
               <p n="7">7. In all thy ways acknowledge God, and he shall direct thy steps, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.6. In all thy ways of buying and selling, trading, eye God in all.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Let thy heart be heavenly in thy civil affairs. Art thou a husband-man, and goest forth to sow? think upon the word; and upon the divers grounds; and examine whether thy soul be like the good ground in the parable; Is there a storm when thou art sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that bringeth tears from thine eys? think of that in <hi>Psal.</hi> 126. <hi>ult.</hi> he that goeth forth and weepeth, bearing precious seed, shall doubtless come again with rejoycing, bringing his sheaves with him. Are thy cattel unruly? Think of thy self, who (as <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.18.) like <hi>Ephraim</hi> hast been as a Bullock unaccustomed to the yoak that as a Bullock unaccustomed to the yoak is unruly, and rings about, and would fain get out, so are our souls at first conversion, when we are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119986:26"/>unaccustomed to the yoak of Christ; but when we come to be accustomed to the yoak of Christ, we finde it easie, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. <hi>ult.</hi> Thus a Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and the poorest labourer, if he have a heavenly gracious spirit, may have sweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, and have his heart inditing some good matter in the midst of his labour and work.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Use the world as if you used it not; let them that have wives be as if they had none; let them that buy do it as if they bought not; sell as if you sold not; using the world as stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and pilgrims, for our necessities in this world, but not abusing it to excess, covetousness, and drawing our souls from Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>If when we are going to prayer, the Lord bringeth some special sin that we have committed, to mind; what a soul may gather from it?</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THe soul may gather this from it, that it doth not lie low enough before God, that the Lord would have the soul more sensible of his own vildness and unworthiness.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:119986:27"/>2. The soul may gather this from it, that the Lord would have the soul pray with much bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenness of heart at that time; the Lord calleth thee especially at such a time to abhor thy self in dust and ashes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It should make us prize the Lord Jesus more, and see our great advantage by him, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding we are such great sinners, that yet we may have access, and draw nigh God with an holy boldness, through the faith of him, that the soul may say, O how I am beholding to Christ, in that I that have committed this and that sin, which might make me for ever be afraid to draw nigh to God with any hope of obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing at his hands, that yet now through his beloved son, in whom he is well pleased. I can at this time seek his face, and pray to him with a holy boldness and confidence.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It should put us upon search and enquiry, that seeing we have committed such and such sins, how we came to have peace of Conscience; and whether length of time took away our trouble of Conscience for them, or we had peace spoken to our souls by the blood of Jesus.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It should put the soul upon this, that see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it hath fallen into such and such sins, as the Lord at that time brought to minde, that the soul should mightily in that duty its about to perform, beseech the Lord to manifest unto him
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119986:27"/>the pardon of all those sins by the blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, and should intreat the Lord for ever to keep him from falling into those sins, desiring the Lord to hold up our goings in his paths, that our footsteps slip not into such ways; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, Lord, my heart is inclining, and I have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny temptations to those sins thou hast now brought to mind, that I have fallen into; Lord, keep me out of these snares of the devil, and order my conversation aright, according to thy Word.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>What the frame of a Christians spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit should be under outward losses and crosses.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. HE must have a care of murmuring and repining at any of Gods dealings, but say, Lord, though I have not in this world whereon to lay my head, yet let me have the light of thy countenance, and I have enough.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Get <hi>Jobs</hi> spirit, who when he had such great outward losses and crosses, said, <hi>The Lord giveth, and the Lord taketh away, blessed be the Name of the Lord,</hi> Job 1. the Lord hath taken
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119986:28"/>away nothing but what he hath first given.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The more outward losses we have, the more it should put us upon chosing the better part, which we can never lose, which can never be taken from us, as Christ told <hi>Mary,</hi> she had chosen the better part, which should never be taken away from her; as for the things of this world, as honour, riches, friends, children, the Lord giveth them, and oftentimes taketh them away again, as he dealt with <hi>Job;</hi> but if the Lord give thee the better part, Jesus Christ, that shall never be taken away; never shall poor soul have cause to say, Lord, thou hast given me Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, and thou hast taken him away again.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When outward losses and crosses come upon-us, we, as <hi>Solomon</hi> saith, in the day of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity should consider; Consider whether thy affections have not formerly run out too much after those things thou hast lost when thou hadst them, and whether thy love was not too much set upon those things thou art crost in; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed its the mercy of God to cross us in those things, that our affections run out so much after, that he may be the object of our love and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light onely.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Do not think God loveth thee not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of thy losses and crosses; for we cannot know love or hatred by the things that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us; and consider that the Lord chasteneth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119986:28"/>every son whom he receiveth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.5, 12. and some have questioned their sonship for want of afflictions, and such losses and crosses as others have met withal; but such may consider,
<list>
                     <item>1. That its a greater affliction then any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward loss or cross, to question their son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship and interest in Christ; so that thou art not without chastisements.</item>
                     <item>2. It may be thou hast made others afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thy own, others sickness thy own, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers poverty thy own, and thus thou maist have had afflictions.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Consider that God doth not afflict willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor grieve the children of men, but as the Apostle saith. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.6. if need be ye are in heaviness; there is always need when we are in heaviness; so let a Christian say, there is need that I should have these losses and crosses, and afflictions, either for the tryal of my faith, or to wean me more from the world, or to humble me, some need there is.</p>
               <p n="7">7 A Christian should not desire to be from under the cross and the affliction, till he see the Lord sanctifying it to him, and doing of him good by it. O this is a hard lesson to learn, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause no affliction for the present is joyous, but grievous; yet this should be the frame of a Christians spirit; Lord thou hast laid this cross upon me, brought this loss upon me; O I do not desire so much to be freed from the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119986:29"/>as to have thy hand sanctified to me, to see that its good for me that I am afflicted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>What a poor Christian should do that is followed with temptations from day to day, and Sathan of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten casts in vain thoughts, and lustful thoughts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SOme into whose hands the Providence of God may bring this book, may groan in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret under these temptations and vain lustfull thoughts, as the greatest burden their souls lie under; therefore let such:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Know, that whatsoever temptations they have, and whatsoever vain and lustful thoughts Sathan casts into their minds, if they do not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain them and close with them, they are not their sins, but their crosses; our Lord Jesus himself, who was without sin, yet he had tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation by the devil, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. saith Satan to him, <hi>Fall down and worship me.</hi> What a black temptation was this, to worship the devil in person; yet the Lord Jesus entertained, closed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119986:29"/>with none of these temptations, and therefore in all these temptations sinned not.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If at any time thou hast given way to vain and lustful thoughts, lie down in thy shame, and let thy soul mourn for it, as for that which is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry evil in the sight of God; who hateth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the filthiness of the flesh, but of the spirit; O let these things make thee walk more humbly with God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In such cases let our souls have recourse to our pittiful and merciful High-Priest, the Lord Jesus, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.17, 18. who is touched with the feeling of our infirmities, and being himself once tempted by the devil, knoweth how to pitty &amp; succour them that are tempted; and the Apostle saith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4 15. that in all points he was tempted as we are, yet without sin. O be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moan thy soul to this thy dear Saviour.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Pray much against vain and lustful thoughts, beseeching the Lord that he would not suffer thee to be tempted above what thou art able, but that with the temptation he would make a way for thy escape out of all the snares of the devil; desire him to be the guide of thy youth, that black and dark age, or else thou wilt finde, as <hi>Solomon</hi> saith, as childhood, so youth, to be full of vanity.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Beware of allowing thy self (in the least) in those vain thoughts, but in the strength of Christ resist the devil, and he will flee from thee,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119986:30"/>do not close with them when they are first cast in, do not give ground to Satan; thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est not what a little fire kindleth. If <hi>David</hi> had not given way to the first stirrings of his lust to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Bathshebah,</hi> he had not faln into that sin of Adultery which cost him so dear.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Shun the occasions of vain and lustfull thoughts; make a covenant with thy eyes, as <hi>Job</hi> did; be not too confident of thy own strength. <hi>David</hi> by gazing upon the beauty of <hi>Bathshebah,</hi> (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2, 3, 4.) fell into those lustfull thoughts, &amp; then into Adultery. <hi>Favour is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and beauty is vanity;</hi> the greatest beauties in the world, when dead a day or two, how loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some are they, and saith <hi>Soloman</hi> (<hi>Prov.</hi> 6.25?) lust not after her beauty in thine heart, O above all keepings keep thy heart, maintain a constant jealousie over thine own heart, lest out of it should (as the Lord Jesus said) proceed evil thoughts, adulteries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Often consider that all things are naked and open to him with whom we have to do; (<hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12, 13,) and that though no man in the world is able to charge us with vain and lustful thoughts, yet the Lord searcheth the hearts, and trieth the reins, and knoweth what is man; hell, and death are before him, much more the hearts of the children of men; he knoweth all the windings and turnings of our souls. <hi>David</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the Lord had rid his heart of vain and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119986:30"/>lustful thoughts, saith he (<hi>Psal.</hi> 139, 23. <hi>Psa.</hi> 26.2.) <hi>Search me O God, and know my heart; try and know my thoughts;</hi> he was not unwilling that the Lord should know his thoughts, but saith he, if there be any wicked way (that is yet left in him) Lord (saith he) lead me in the way everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Consider that those vain thoughts hinder there of communion with God; if thou givest way to vain and lustful thoughts, shall not God search this out, (<hi>Psal.</hi> 44.21) who knoweth the secrets of the heart? and will not he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the light of his countenance? O then how will the troubles of thy heart be inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>How a Christian should carry him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, when the Providence of God casteth him among carnal and prophane people.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. DEsire of God that thou maist be kept from sinning against him; for we are in much danger when we are among carnal peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119986:31"/>as <hi>Peter,</hi> when he was among those pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane creatures in the high Priests Hall, denied the Lord Jesus.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Be careful of thy carriage, that thou countenance them not in their sins, but let thy carriage bear witness against their sinfull ways.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If thou faist any thing among them, let thy speech be such as may administer grace to the hearer; and yet thou wilt find this very difficult, for <hi>David,</hi> that eminent man saith, (<hi>Psal.</hi> 39.) he refained himself even from good, whilst the wicked were before him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let thy carriage be such among them, that they may see that thou canst not run into the same excess of riot with them, the fear of the Lord is so upon thy heart.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Let thy carriage be winning, that thou mayst present Religion lovely, and bring them to an esteem of the wayes and people of God.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If thou seest them prophane and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of God, let it put thee upon thankfulness to thy God, who hath delivered thee from the power of darkness, and translated thee into the kingdom of his dear son, and hath taken off thy soul from living in prophaneness and enmity against him.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If they be full of carnal mirth and jollity, and thou seest them so pleasant, beware of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119986:31"/>hankering after the Garlick and Onions of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> and thy sinful pleasures that thou didst en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy in thy natural condition, but think with thy self, all these things have I forsaken for Christs sake, and I never repent of it, my soul hath bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter joys and delights then these.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Let thy heart be pittiful and compassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate towards them, and let thy soul desire their good, as <hi>Paul</hi> when he came among those ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people, and King <hi>Agrippa</hi> told him, Thou almost perswadedest me to be a Christian; saith he, I would that not onely almost, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together thou wert as I am, except these bonds; so let thy soul desire, if it be the will of God, that they were as thou art, except thy bonds, thy temptations, coruptions, doubtings.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Let him mourn for their prophaneness and wickedness, as it was with <hi>David;</hi> tears run down my eys, saith he, because men keep not thy law; and as it was with <hi>Lot,</hi> his gracious heart was grieved to hear and see how sinful they were in <hi>Sodom.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:119986:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>What a Christians frame should be under the reproaches of the world, when the world speaketh evil of us, and rail on us.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. HAve a care that the world have not cause to speak evil of us as of evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that we suffer as Saints, and not as sinners.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The more the men of the world spie and prie into our wayes, and slander and reproach; the more we should pray, with <hi>David,</hi> (<hi>Psal.</hi> 5.8.) that the Lord would lead us in wayes of plainness, because of our observers, as the word signifieth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Make good use of their reproaches, and get good by their evil; let their slanders and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches make us walk the more circumspectly, not as fools, but as wise, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.15.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let a Christian in this case consider that our Lord Jesus himself was reproached, called <hi>Belzebub,</hi> deceiver; and is the Disciple above his Master? If (saith the Lord Iesus) they have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the master of the house <hi>Belzebub,</hi> how much more them of his houshold, and let him consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119986:32"/>that the Saints all along, though they are those of whom the world is not worthy, yet they have been counted the off-scouring of all things. <hi>Paul</hi> is charged by the world for Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, as the people of God at this day are counted Hereticks, and Schismaticks; but after the way that the world calls Heresie, worship we the God of our fathers.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Look beyond the instrument; as when <hi>Shimei</hi> railed and cursed <hi>David</hi> so bitterly, saith he, when they that were with him would have kild him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. he saith, let him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; he looked at the hand of God in it; and though <hi>Shimei</hi> did reproach in so high a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and he a King, and calleth him bloody man, and man of Belial: yet eying God in it, he seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no revenge; yea though <hi>Shimei</hi> went so far as to throw stones at <hi>David</hi> (as some of Gods people, as they have gone through some Towns, have had stones to my knowledge thrown at them) yet <hi>David</hi> is patiently carried forth, and so shall we in such cases, if we look at he hand of God in all, and know that all these things shall work for our good.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Have a care thou doest not neglect pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for thy enemies, and them that hate thee, and speak evil of thee for Jesus sake; do not render evil for evil unto any man, nor railing for railing; but bless them that curse you, and pray for them that despightfully use you; you
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119986:33"/>know not but God may give them repentance to the acknowledgement of the truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>What a Christians frame should be, if he be unequally yoaked; as if a believing husband hath an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing Wife, or a believing Wife hath an unbelieving Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis hath been the affliction of many Saints, as holy <hi>Job</hi> that had a wife that would have him curse God and die;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>And</hi> Samson, <hi>how unequally yoaked was he.</hi>
                  </note> and a Christian may come to be une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually yoaked, either that they may be mistaken, and think they marry in the Lord, and it prove contrary to their expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or the Lord may work upon the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band or the Wife after their coming together; therefore to such as come thus to be unequally yoaked,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let thy conversation be winning; the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Husband doth not know but that he
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119986:33"/>may gain his Wife, and the believing Wise doth not know but she may win her Husband; as the Apostle saith, that the believing wives should have such chaste conversations, and be of such meek and quiet spirits, that those who are not won by the Word, that is, by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Gospel, that they may be won by the conversation of the wives; now when the Husband is a professor, and is unkinde and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to his wife, it doth harden the wifes heart in the ways of sin, and prejudice her against the wayes of God; and so if the wife be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessor, if that she do not obey her husband in all lawful things, and if she be not of a meek and quiet patient Spirit, it doth prejudice the ways of God, and presents Religion unlovely to him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Pray much for thy Husband, or for thy Wife, to whom thou art thus unequally yoaked. <hi>Abraham</hi> prayed for his son <hi>Ishmael;</hi> O saith he, that <hi>Ishmael</hi> might live in thy sight. Now the Husband and wife are neerer then a childe to a father; for the Husband and Wife are one flesh; and O how should they wrestle with God! O that my Husband, or, O that my Wife might live in thy sight!</p>
               <p n="3">3. Desire of the Lord that thou mayst not be hindered in serving God by thy husband or wife, that are thus unbelieving; and that thou mayest not be prejudiced in the thriving and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119986:34"/>prospering of thy soul in the wayes of God, as holy <hi>Job</hi> would not be drawn by his Wife (<hi>Job</hi> 2.9.10.) to curse God and die; No saith he; Shall we receive good at the hands of the Lord, and not evil? Remember <hi>Solomon,</hi> into what great sins he fell by reason of his unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving wives.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Admire the Free-grace of God, which alone maketh you to differ, that of two that lie in a bed, the one should be taken, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther left.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Waite upon God to see that Promise made good to thee, that all things shall work together for good to them that love God, who are the called according to his Promise, and that thou maist see God doing thee good by this sad Providence which thou shouldst ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the greatest outward affliction that can befall thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119986:34"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>How a Christians thoughts should be exercised about death, and his putting off this Tabernacle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE shall finde in the Scriptures that the Saints thoughts were much exercised upon death; and these things should be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Saints spirit in his Meditations upon death.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He should pray with <hi>David;</hi> that the Lord would teach him so to number his dayes, that he may apply his heart unto wisdom; that his busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in this world may be to grow in Grace, and the knowledge of the Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Christian should often consider, that here he hath no continuing City, but as <hi>Iob</hi> said, I know thou wilt bring me unto death, unto the house appointed for all living; let not a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian think of long life; it is appointed to all men once to die, to the Saints as well as others; these houses of clay will soon fall down.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Christian should often act faith for his dying day, when his soul enjoyeth communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God, as now the Lord is pleased to lift up the light of his countenance upon my soul,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119986:35"/>and now as I were to die the next hour, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that I am justified freely by his Grace, and that I shall sleep in Jesus. <hi>Paul</hi> when he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed communion with God and the witness of the Spirit, doth act faith for his dying day; and faith he, We know that when these earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tabernacles shall be dissolved, we have houses not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens; (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1) and a soul that doth thus act faith for his dying day, death is no strange thing to him; for he can say with the Apostle, I know whom I have believed, I know in whose bosome I have so often lain, whom I have trusted my eternal condition withal.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A Christian should wait all the days of his appointed time until his change shall come, (<hi>Iob</hi> 24.14.) that so when death shall come, he may say, welcom Death, I have waited ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeers for thee, thou art welcome to me, thou art a messenger sent from my Father to fetch me home, to bring me unto my Saviours bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A Christian should not desire to live one hour in this world (to enjoy any pleasures and contentments here below) longer then he hath served his God and his generation, according to his will: but should say, if my work be done, for which the Lord sent me into the world, O that I were dissolved to be with Christ, which is best of all.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119986:35"/>6. Let a Christian often consider what great gain it will be to him to die; now he knoweth but in part; then he shall know as he is known, and see God face to face, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.) now he laboureth under weaknesses and corruptions; then he shall never sin more. O long for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that we may have better hearts; then we may say to sin, whether I go thou canst not come; now many a time he wants communion with God, and hath but little joy in the Spirit; then he shall have fulness of joy and pleasures for evermore: thus a Christians thoughts should be exercised about death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>How Christians should carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves towards their Brethren, when their Brethren are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken with a fault, and fall into some sin.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. AS the Apostle saith, If any be overta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with a fault, ye that are spiritual restore such a one with the spirit of meekness, (<hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1.) considering thy self, lest thou also
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119986:36"/>be tempted; Dost thou see thy fellow Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an fall into sin? Consider thy self, lest thou also if thou be tempted as he was, if that the Lord do not keep thee, fall as well as he.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As Christs rule directs thee, go and tell him between him and thee, do not speak of it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, until thou hast told him of his miscarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges between him and thee; but afterwards if he will not hear thee, then take two or three Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians; and if he will not hear them, go tell the Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thou shalt not hate thy brother in thy heart, nor suffer sin upon him; if thou sufferest sin upon thy brother, and dost not reprove him for it, thou hatest him in thy heart. O that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians may be faithful one to another.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Pray for them, that the Lord would heal their back-slidings, take away all their iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and recover them out of the snares of the devil.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Speak not of their miscarriages before the men of the world, who would be glad of any occasion to speak evil of those that walk in the paths of Sion.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Do not censure them, and think them not to be Saints, because of some failings, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how those eminent Saints of God had their failings; <hi>Lot</hi> committed Incest, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> Adultery and Murther; <hi>Peter,</hi> denyed the Lord Jesus; Consider what the Apostle
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119986:36"/>saith, <hi>In many things we offend all;</hi> not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in some few things, but in many things; every one standeth or falleth to his own Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster; who art thou that judgest thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
               <p n="7">7. Take occasion from the miscarriages of other Christians, to be more watchful over thy self; it may be thy brother that hath miscarried, is of greater Gifts, Experiences, and Graces then thy self; O then, how hadst thou need to watch and pray; if a <hi>David</hi> commit Adultery, If a <hi>Peter</hi> deny Christ, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what cause have I, the least of all Saints, to be watchful, and to wrestle with God, to keep me from sinning against hm!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:119986:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>Whether a Christian ought to keep the first day of the week holy unto the Lord as a Gospel Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WIthin these few yeers many Professors have I taken much liberty as to the breaking of the Gospel-Sabbath; now such will say, Is not every day a Sabbath to a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. As for resting from sin, every day should be a Sabbath to a believer, and he should cease from his own work, as God did from his, and we should all labour to enter into that Rest, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.10, 11.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Gospel-Sabbath doth imply a Rest not onely from sin, and in God, but also a Rest from bodily labour; and therefore when we shall spend that everlasting Sabbath in Glory, the Scripture saith, We shall rest from our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; and then if every day were in this sense a Sabbath to a Believer, a Believer should never work.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You shall observe this on such professors,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119986:37"/>that when their Sabbath observation cometh from one day to every day, it soon cometh from every day to no day, and you shall finde them to be very remiss in holy duties every day.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As for that Rest the Saints have in God, doth the observing of the first day in the week holy to the Lord, doth this I say hinder, or doth it not further this spiritual Rest, or Communion with God?</p>
               <p>I wonder not at all to see the prophane of the world make no Conscience of keeping the first day of the week holy to the Lord; but when professors do so, I much admire; and though they may think they are more spiritual then others; yet if they well consider, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the flesh, and carnality; for when as a Christian riseth early the first day of the week, and spends the whole day in the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the things of God, and in praying, hearing, spiritual conference, self-examination, the spirit is willing to all this, but the flesh is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing, and cryeth, O what a bondage is it! O what a weariness is it! And the flesh would fain be set at liberty from this keeping of a day holy, and wholly unto the Lord. Let Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans be as spiritual as they can, and worship God in spirit and in truth, as much as they can, this is from the Spirit: But to cast off the observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the day to the Lord, and to speak their own words, and take liberty otherways, ariseth
<pb facs="tcp:119986:38"/>from the flesh; and perswasion that we have this liberty, cometh not of him that calleth us.</p>
               <p>I shall forbear the pressing of those proofs for the observation of that day, from Christs rising from the dead on that day, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles and Saints constant meeting on that day, and <hi>Johns</hi> calling it the Lords-Day, as also the Circumcising under the Law on the eighth day, which may hold out the Circumcising the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skin of the heart on the first day of the week, which is the eighth day; I say, I forbear to press these things, which have been urged by others, which seem to be very weighty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>What a Christian should do in time of National troubles, wars, and uproars.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. LEt him pray for the Nation, that the Lord would give us peace, if it be his will, and that we may sit down quietly under our own Vines, speaking well of his Name.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let a Christian be waiting to see all these shakings of the Nations make way for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of all Nations to come (<hi>Hag.</hi> 2.7.) and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119986:38"/>take to him his great power and reign; there are sons and daughters of Sion in this Nation, that in all the wars and publick distractions amongst us, have been waiting for that day of Christs reigning in Mount Sion, and their spirits cried out, overturn, overturn, overturn, Kings, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, until he shall come whose right it is.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Let not Christians in time of war and National troubles, be afraid of evil tidings, but let their hearts be fixed, standing still to see the salvation of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let them make sure of a hiding place; get the Lord to be your refuge from the storm, that he may say, as <hi>Isa.</hi> 26. <hi>ult.</hi> Come my people, enter into your Chamber, and shut the door a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you until my indignation be overpast; the Name of the Lord is a strong Tower; and in time of war, if men know of a strong Tower, they will run to it; and therefore <hi>David</hi> having said, that the Name of the Lord was a strong Tower, saith he, the righteous run to it and are safe, <hi>Psal.</hi> 27.5.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Lord eminently calleth thee to fit loose from the creature; for in a night thy dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est relations may be taken from thee; all thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state; now if thou hast Christ, thou hast trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure laid up in Heaven, where neither Moth can corrupt, nor Thieves break through and steal.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:119986:39"/>6. Let it be the desire of thy soul in time of National troubles, that it may go well with the people of God, that the eternal God would be their refuge.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Live by Faith, and in constant depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon God, and commit thy self to him; cast thy care upon the Lord, for he careth for thee.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Let outward war put thee upon looking more after thy inward peace; Oh I see in the Nations war and destruction! O have I peace in my own soul! have I peace spoken to my soul by the blood of Jesus! and if a poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have the peace of God, which passeth all understanding, it will keep his heart in a spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al cheerful frame in the midst of all these storms and tempests in the world. I see what a boiste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous troublesome sea this world is; O how do I rejoyce that my name is written in Heaven, that is the better Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:119986:39"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>How a believer ought to mourn for sin.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. NEgatively, 1. Not for fear of Hell and damnation; The smoak of hell must not bring forth tears from his eys; a <hi>Judas</hi> may mourn for sin, as that for which he feareth he shall be damned.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A believer should not mourn for sin, as thinking by his tears and sorrow to procure the pardon of his sins; he must seek that onely from Christ, in whom we have redemption through his blood, even the forgiveness of sins; The dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Hell will weep and shed rivers of tears; yet they will not all wash them from the least sin; the blood of Christ onely cleanseth from sin, (1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7.) we must not make a Christ of our tears, and think to do that by our tears, which the blood of Christ onely can do. O how many Physitians of no value, when souls are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for sin, will still bid them mourn for their sins, and God will pardon them, and not a word of Christ; and then how is the poor soul insnared! he taketh the advice that is given him, and mourneth for his sins upon this account,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119986:40"/>that he is perswaded if he mourn for them, they shall be pardoned; and so is still ignorant of Christ, and seeth not sin in its right colours, neither doth mourn aright for sin.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Positively. 1. A believer should mourn for sin because its so hateful to our heavenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the great hatred that God hath against sin, he exprest it in the death of Christ, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. for sin he condemned sin in the flesh, that is to say, though the dear son of God undertake for sin, yet it was so hateful to him, that he doth not spare his own son, but condemneth sin in the flesh of Christ, that Christ must die and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, and have the face of God hid from him for our sins; now saith a believer, is sin so hateful to my God and father? and did the Lord Jesus suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer so much for my sins? O this sin! O what an evil sin is! O that ever I should do that which is so hateful, so displeasing unto my God! O how doth it trouble me! O how doth it grieve me more then the loss of an onely son!</p>
               <p n="2">2. A believers heart should be melted by the goodness of God; the beams of the Son of righteousness should melt our frozen hearts; the goodness of God should lead us to repentance (<hi>Rom.</hi> 2.) O hath the Lord pluckt me as a fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand out of the fire! not spared his own son, but delivered him up to death for me! O that I should ever offend and dishonour this father of mercies! O what an unworthy wretch am I,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119986:40"/>to make such ill requitals of his love! I lie down in my shame; Lord I abhor my self in dust and ashes, that ever I should sin against thee; O that I should sin against thee my father, who hast loved me with an everlasting love, followed me with thy Mercies! O what a base heart have I!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIX. <hi>How a soul may know whether his assurance be right or no.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis is of great consequence; most men, even the prophanest creatures, believe they shall be saved; therefore its of great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to know whether our assurance be right or no, which I shall inquire into by these fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing particulars, which the experiences of Christians will enlarge.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Then its the Spirit of Christ that sealeth us to the day of Redemption; the Spirit of Christ witnesseth with our Spirits that we are the sons and daughters of God (<hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1 16.) if our assurance be right, as the Apostle saith, After ye believed, ye were sealed by the holy spirit of promise; our assurance of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119986:41"/>is not currant, if it hath not the Spirits seal.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Spirit of Christ when it doth witness with our Spirits that we are sons of God, doth also bear witness to the work of God upon our hearts, that it is a true work, and that the Lord hath been pleased to work those things in us which accompany salvation; and therefore those that are not born again, and have not the good work begun in their hearts, have not a true assurance.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If our assurance be right, it proceedeth not from our own righteousness; not because I am so and so holy; therefore I am sure I shall be saved: But the Lord hath loved me freely, given his son for me, and to me; whose blood cleanseth me from all sin: I am not made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in my self, I am the greatest of sinners, but I am made acceptable in the beloved. <hi>John</hi> saith, He that believeth hath the witness in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, that is, the spirit of Christ that dwelleth in the Saints; but though we have the witness in our selves, yet not from our selves; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if our assurance be drawn from our own righteousness, as those that are of the Law think they have a good assurance of heaven from their own righteousness, this assurance is naught.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If our assurance be right, it will make the soul walk humbly with God, and cause Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel sorrow for sin; the more assurance we have that our sins are pardoned, the more we
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119986:41"/>mourn for sin, and therefore when the Lord hath given in such a good word to a soul, as I am thy salvation, I have blotted out as a thick cloud, thy transgressions, and will remember thy sins no more, O saith the believing soul, Hath the Lord healed my backslidings, been mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to my unrighteousness? O what an unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy wretch am I, that ever I should sin against such a God!</p>
               <p n="5">5. If our assurance be right, it will make the soul have dear love to God and Christ. <hi>We,</hi> saith the Apostle, <hi>love him, because he first loved us,</hi> (1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.) the knowledge of the love of God and Christ to us, will work the love of God and Christ in us; how can a soul but love God, when he knoweth its his pleasure to give him a kingdom?</p>
               <p n="6">6. If our assurance be right, it will make the soul active for God; when <hi>David</hi> had assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the love of God, saith he, What shall I render to the Lord for all his benefits? and saith he, Thou hast delivered my soul from death, mine eyes from tears, and my feet from falling; there was his assurance of the love of God; and what did this work upon <hi>Davids</hi> Spirit? why it followeth, I am thy servant, I am thy servant; as if he had said, Lord, now I know thy loving kindness to my soul, O how I am engaged to live to thee, and lay out my self for thee! Lord shew me but wherein I may bring any glory to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119986:42"/>thy great Name, and I am thy servant to spend and be spent for thee.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If our assurance be right, the greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree we have of it, the more holy; if any think they have assurance of the love of God, and that nothing shall seperate them from the love of Christ; if they take heart to sin, from that perswasion, its a plain sign their assurance of the love of Christ is not from the Spirit of Christ, but rather from the spirit that ruleth in the children of disobedience; the spirit of Christ is a spirit of godliness, and maketh the soul which it seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the day of Redemption, say, I have assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the inheritance with Saints in light; and therefore now what have I to do with the unfruitful works of darkness? <hi>Hos.</hi> 14.4, 5. saith God, <hi>I will heal their back-slidings, and I will be as the dew unto them,</hi> and saith the Lord, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>Ephraim</hi> shall say, <hi>What have I to do any more with Idols?</hi> so saith a soul that hath a true assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the love of God, and that he hath healed his back-slidings, what have I to do any more with Idols? What have I to do any more with drunkenness, swearing, covetousness, self-seeking? and 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.23. He that hath this hope, purifyeth himself as he is pure.</p>
               <p n="8">8. If our assurance be right, it will make us more spiritual in our obedience; we do not now do good works, thinking to be saved by them; no we are assured by the spirit, that we
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119986:42"/>are saved freely by grace; and therefore now we do good works because the Lord hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen us, that we might be holy, and because this is the will of God concerning us; we do not then do good works to make us Ladders to Heaven, as those of the Law do.</p>
               <p n="9">9. If our assurance be right, it will dead our hearts to the world, and to all the imaginations here below; when a soul hath assurance of spend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eternity with God, he is mightily taken off from setting his affections on things below; O saith he, I have treasure laid up in Heaven, I have in Heaven a more durable substance then any thing in this world; and therefore I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at some, who pretend to much assurance of the love of God, and of spending eternity with God, and yet are so earthly, covetous, self-seeking: O if their assurance were right, it would make them have their conversation more in Heaven, and set light by the world, saying, I have assurance of a better portion, the Lord himself is my portion.</p>
               <p n="10">10. If our assurance be right, it will help us to bear afflictions, losses, and crosses in this world with great ease; it maketh the soul say, I know that all things shall work together for my good, and that though the Lord prove me and try me, yet he will do me good in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end; and I having assurance of his love, this quiets my heart in all his dealings; and what
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119986:43"/>though I have not outward riches? saith such a soul; yet I have the pearl of great price, the Lord Jesus; what though I have not a house of my own in this world? yet I know that when this earthly Tabernacle shall be dissolved, I have a house not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.) and because assurance of the love of God doth make afflictions and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings so easie; therefore in time of sufferings the Lord usually giveth the Saints this assurance, which maketh a prison a palace; what Saint e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was in prison for Christ, but Christ came to visit him, and kist him with the kisses of his love.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>Concerning doubtings and their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. WHat is the cause of the Saints doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and questioning the love of God to their souls?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Cause of doubtings is ignorance of the covenant of Grace, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. I will be merciful to their unrighteousness; and saith <hi>David,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though mine house be not so with God, yet he
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119986:43"/>hath made an everlasting Covenant with me, established in all things, and sure, though he make it not to grow; a Saints falling into sin, would not make him think himself a damned creature, if there were not an ignorance of the Covenant of Grace; for might the soul say, although my heart be not so with God as it should be, though I be not so holy as I should be, yet hath he made with me an everlasting Covenant, established in all things; and sure its of grace, saith the Apostle, that it might be sure to all the seed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Cause of doubting is our not keeping of our eyes upon Christ, as its said in the Prophet, they forgat their resting place; Christ is the Saints resting place; and needs must the Saints be weary, heavy laden, if they keep not their eye upon Christ; the neglecting of the acting of faith on the blood of Christ after falling into sin, is very dangerous, and is one cause of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Cause of doubting is hearkening what Sathan saith; Sathan he suggests, that thou art a damned creature, forsaken of God; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if thou hearken to what he saith, thou must needs fall into doubtings; saith <hi>David, Psal.</hi> 85.8. <hi>I will hear what the Lord will say, for he will speak peace to his people;</hi> and so will the devil speak peace to his people; but if the Saints will hear what the devil saith, he will tell them they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119986:44"/>are lost, and their portion shall be to sit down with the damned in hell.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Cause of doubtings, is the not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring our former experiences; and therefore <hi>David</hi> to get out of doubtings, called to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance his song in the night; so should a Saint; its now a sad time with me, my dear Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour hath withdrawn himself; yet I remember my song in the night, how in such a place, at such a time, in such a condition, what sweet communion I had with God, and assurance of his love.</p>
               <p>Now we have shown the cause of doubtings, I shall speak a few words of advice to Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that are under doubtings.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That of the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> is very season<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, <hi>Who is among you that feareth the Lord, and obeyeth the voice of his servant, and walketh in darkness, and seeth no light? let him trust in the name of the Lord, and stay himself upon his God</hi> (<hi>Isa.</hi> 50.10) as <hi>Iob</hi> said, <hi>Though he kill me, yet will I put my trust in him;</hi> and indeed there is faith in the Saints in the midst of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Seek after Christ, as the Spouse did when her beloved had withdrawn himself; seek Christ in praying, hearing, conference with aints, reading, meditating, and all the wayes of Christ.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:119986:44"/>3. Often consider, that the most eminent Saints have had doubtings, and have questioned the love of God to their souls; and yet though the Lord hath hid his face from them for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet in everlasting loving kindness he hath received them, as we may instance in <hi>Job,</hi> who complains, That the Arrows of the Almighty stuck fast within him, and the terrours of the Almighty made him afraid; and likewise <hi>David</hi> complaineth that his sins were gone over his head, and became a burden too heavy for him to bear (<hi>Psal.</hi> 38.4.) and saith he, the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of my heart are enlarged; and he thought that God had forgotten to be gracious, and would smile no more; and so <hi>Heman</hi> complains, (<hi>Psal.</hi> 8.8.) that his soul was full of troubles, and crieth out, <hi>Lord why castest thou off my soul, why hidest thou thy face from me?</hi> let a soul con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider these things, and say not there is no hope: the Lord hath hid his face from many of his children, and they have been in doubtings as well as thou, and yet the Lord in his time hath given them a fuller assurance of his love then ever.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Meditate much upon free-grace: how do souls that lie under doubtings, as the Prophet saith, meditate terrours? O thy soul should me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate much on free-grace, and the promises of the Gospel, as that in <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me all ye that are weary and heavy-laden, and I
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119986:45"/>will give you rest,</hi> here thy dear Saviour calleth thee into his bosome.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Frequent the company of the Saints much, it may please the Lord to create the fruit of their lips peace to thy troubled heart; if the Lord please, they may come to comfort thee with the comforts wherewith they have been comforted of God, when they have been in the same con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that thou art now in.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Be often meditating upon those promises by which the Lord hath spoken peace to thee heretofore, as many Saints can tell; which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises the Lord hath sometimes made sweeter then the hony and the hony-comb; now though till the Lord speak again to thy soul by them, they will be but dry breasts to thy soul, yet thou knowest not how soon the Lord may speak to thee by them, and let thee draw waters with the buckets of faith out of those wells of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:119986:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXI. <hi>What a Christian should do that finds not so much of the assistance of the Spirit in prayer, as he was wont, is not so enlarged in Prayer as he was wont.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. EXamine whether thou hast not been proud of enlargement in prayer, and whether thou hast not regarded enlargement in Prayer as to expressions, more then communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God in prayer, and the answers of thy prayers: it may be thou hast not minded what hath become of thy prayers, whether the Lord answer them or no: but if thou hast been inlarged as to expressions, thou hast minded the other things but little; now the Lord, to let thee see thy great folly in this, withdraws the assistance of his Spirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Examine whether thou dost not go out in thy own strength, and not in the strength of the Spirit of Christ.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Learn to make a right estimate of thy praying; the Spirit of Christ may assist us in prayer, when we are not so much enlarged as to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119986:46"/>expressions, for as the Apostle saith (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.36) The Spirit maketh intercession for us with sighs and with groans that cannot be uttered; which sighs and groans of the Spirit of Christ in us, lie as nigh God as the most excellent expressions that can come from us in prayer; yea and are more prevalent with God, unless they come from the same spirit; therefore let not a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian think that he alwayes prays best, when he hath best expressions; but the more thou prayest in faith, the better thou prayest; the more brokenness of heart in prayer, the better thou prayest; the more thou prayest in the Spirit, and with understanding, and fervently, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thou prayest; a Christian sometimes pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and is much enlarged in expressions, and they that are present think he prays excellently, but he thinketh that he had not so much of the assistance of the Spirit at that time as at some other time, when yet he hath been more strait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as to expression.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Art not thou so much enlarged in prayer, as thou wert wont? consider whether it be that thou art straitned in private prayer, or in fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or publick; if thou beest straitned in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate prayer, examine whether thou hast not neglected private prayer too much.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:119986:46"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXII. <hi>Some advice to poor Christians that complain much of ignorance, that they know no more of Christ.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are but few of these that thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of ignorance and shortness; but some I know that do thus complain, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would speak something that might be use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let such acknowledge it a mercy that they are sensible of their ignorance and short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, that they do not think they know enough of Christ.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Ask wisdom and knowledge of God, who giveth liberally and upbraideth not (<hi>Jam.</hi> 1.5.) saying unto him, Lord, what I know not, teach thou me; wherein I am dark, ignorant, low, and fall short, O do thou reveal even that unto me! O that the eyes of my understanding may be enlightned, that I may know the mysterie of thy will, that unto me it may be given to know the mysterie of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom! (<hi>Mat.</hi> 31.11.) Lord, that I may experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally know more of the beauty of Christ, and that I know more of the usefulness of Christ, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119986:47"/>that I may know more of the preciousness of Christ, and that I may know more of the love of Christ that passeth knowledge, that I may be filled with all the fulness of God!</p>
               <p n="3">3. Do not sit down in your small measure of knowledge, so as not to press after growth and increase, but be following on to know the Lord, pressing forwards towards the mark of the high calling of God in Jesus Christ our Lord (<hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14.) growing in grace, and the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ; do not say, I know enough of Christ to bring me to Heaven; but forgetting those things that are behinde, press forwards, if by any means thou maist attain to the resurrection of the dead, that is to say, if by any means thou maist attain that communion with God, and perfect knowledge of God and Christ, that the Saints shall have at the resurrection of the dead.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Make use of all helps and means to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease thy knowledge of Christ, and the good wayes and things of God; use all means, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hearing, reading, Christian conference, and trust in none; be most acquainted with those who are most acquainted with Christ; and the Ordinances are means to increase our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Christ, as he saith, (<hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13.) <hi>He gave some Apostles, some Prophets, some E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelists, and some Pastors and Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119986:47"/>Ministry, for the edifying of the body of Christ, till we all come in the unity of the faith of the knowledge of the Son of God unto perfect men;</hi> so that the Lord is pleased to appear so in the Ordinances, that his people come by his bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing upon them, to the knowledge of the Son of God to a perfect man; therefore let Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians that complain of their having but little knowledge of Christ, wait upon God in the use of means.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Let those Christians that complain of spiritual ignorance, consider, that in this life, those that have most knowledge, know but in part, and see but as thorow a glass darkly, as the Apostle saith, The best Saints here lie in a great deal of darkness.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Long for Heaven, and that Rest for the people of God; for though we here see as through a glass darkly, yet there we shall see face to face (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12 <hi>ult.)</hi> here we know but in part; there we shall know as we are known, and see Christ as he is; there is much in that expression, <hi>know as we are known;</hi> all those things that we now know but in part, as the mysterie of our union with Christ, how we are joyned to the Lord, and are one spirit, and such like mysteries, here we know but little of these things; but then we shall know them fully; then we shall know the beauty of Christ fully, when we shall see him face to face.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:119986:48"/>7. Desire of the Lord, that though he hath not been pleased to give thee so much know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as he hath given some of his people, that yet he would be pleased to sanctifie that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge he hath given thee, that thou maist honour him, walk with him according to that light thou hast; and indeed we shall see some Christians that have less knowledge in the notion, walk more closely with God, are more consciencious, self-denying, then many that are high in noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, pretending to greater knowledge in the mysterie of Christ, and will tell these poor Christians they are in the dark: O let Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans be faithful unto that light God hath given them!</p>
               <p n="8">8. Beware of envying those to whom the Lord hath given more light and knowledge then he hath given to you; such as have but a small measure of the knowledge of Jesus Christ, are very liable to this temptation of envying others that have more knowledge then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; but let not thy eye be evil because the Lord is good.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Be perswaded that thou art never the less beloved of Christ, because he hath not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thee so much knowledge of himself as he hath given to others: as to thy Saintship, do not look so much at the degrees of thy know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as at the truth of thy knowledge, <hi>(Ioh.</hi> 17.3.) this is eternal life to know thee the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119986:48"/>true God, and Jesus Christ whom he hath sent; the Text doth not say its eternal life to know God and Christ as much as <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Peter</hi> did, but if thou hast a true experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal sanctified knowledge of the Father and of Christ, thou art as sure of eternal life as those that have most, and art as much in the love Christ, who will not quench the smoaking Flaxe, nor break the bruised Reed, but knoweth how to have compassion on the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Beware that thy desires be not more after Gifts then Grace, more after knowledge of Christ then after Christ himself; if thou hadst gifts and knowledge as much as any, would that satisfie thee, though thou hadst less love to Christ, and less communion with Christ, and less of the fear of God in thy heart? beware of this snare of the devil.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:119986:49"/>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:119986:49"/>
            <head>THE GLORIOUS PRIVILEDGES of them that are CHRISTS.</head>
            <head type="sub">Sermon. I.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 3.29.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And if ye be Christs, then are ye <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed, and heirs according to the Promise.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Epistle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> is as it were an Epitome or sum of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle to the <hi>Romans;</hi> In both which Epistles, the Apostles chief aim is to cleer the Doctrine of Justificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>freely by Grace, without the works of the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119986:50"/>Law,</hi> and in this <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 6. sheweth how <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> believed, and and it was accounted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for righteousness; <hi>it,</hi> that is to say, the righteousness of Christ was accounted unto him for righteousness, and <hi>v.</hi> 7. Know ye, saith he, that those who are of faith, the same are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of faithful <hi>Abraham;</hi> those who are of the Law, are not <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed, nor heirs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the promise; and <hi>v.</hi> 18. there is neither Jew nor Greek, bond nor free, male nor female, but ye are all one in Christ Jesus; the business is not whether ye shall be Jews or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, bond, or free, male, or female; but the great business to enquire after is, whether you be Christs, and if indeed ye be Christs, then saith he, Ye are <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed, and heirs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the promise.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That all Divine Priviledges, Heaven, and Happiness, belong to them that are Christs, and to them onely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the opening of this truth, I shall shew you,</p>
            <p n="1">1. What it is to be Christs. — Secondly why divine Priviledges, heaven and happiness, belongs to them that are Christs, and to them onely.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Shew what are the Glorious Priviledges of those that are Christs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Shew you how you may know whether you are Christs or no.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:119986:50"/>5. Make use of this point.</p>
            <p>For the first, What it is to be Christs,</p>
            <p>This is held forth in the Scripture by being,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Christs seed. The Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> speaking of Christ, saith he, <hi>When thou shalt make his soul an offering for sin, he shall see his seed; he shall prolong his days, and the pleasure of the Lord shall prosper in his hands;</hi> now saith the Apostle, If you be Christs, if you be Christs seed, then are you of the spiritual seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and heirs according to the promise.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Christs children; Behold I and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that God hath given me; as if the Apostle had told the <hi>Galatians,</hi> All your works, perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, own righteousness, will never bring you to the inheritance of the Saints in light; but if you be Christs, if you be Christs children, if Christ be formed in you, if ye be children of that <hi>everlasting father, and prince of Peace,</hi> then ye are heirs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Isai.</hi> 9.6.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Christs Brethren; both he that sanctifyeth, and they that are sanctified, are all of one; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, saith the Apostle, He is not ashamed to call them Brethren, (<hi>Heb.</hi> 2.11.) The Saints are called Christs brethren; the blessed God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, he is their Father; as the Lord Jesus said to <hi>Mary</hi> before his Ascension, Go to my Brethren, and say unto them, <hi>I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend unto my Father and your Father, (Joh.</hi> 20.17.) Now saith the Apostle, If you be Christs,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119986:51"/>that is to say, Christs Brethren, that so you and Christ have all one Father, and so you are sons, why as the Apostle saith, If sons, then heirs, heirs of God, and joint-heirs with Christ, that is to say, co-heirs with the Lord Jesus our El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der brother.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Christs Church and spouse; the Church <hi>is the Bride, the Lambs Wife, (Rev,</hi> 19.7 <hi>c.</hi> 21.9.) the Church of the first-born, they are the heirs according to the promise; as if the Apostle had said, If ye be dead to the Law, and are married unto another Husband, even to him who was raised from the dead, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4.) that is the Lord Jesus, that so you are Christs spouses, then you shall have that immortal crown of Glory, else you will never have it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Christs sheep; my sheep saith Christ, hear my voice, (<hi>Joh.</hi> 10.27) If you be Christs sheep, if you be of that little flock to whom its the fathers pleasure to give the kingdom, then you are blessed men and women, then you are heirs indeed.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Christs people; <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.21. you read of Christs people; the men of the world, they have their portion in this life, spend their days in pleasure, and leave their substance unto their Babes, but in a moment they go down to the grave, and then they are turned into Hell, where the worm dieth not, and the fire goeth not out; but if ye be Christs, if you are the people of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119986:51"/>Jesus, then you are heir according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, saith the Text, You shall reign in life by one Jesus Christ.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Christs servants; The devil hath his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, the world hath his servants, and the lusts of the flesh have thair servants; there is never a lust but hath abundance of servants in the world, lust pride hath abundance of servants, lust-covetousness, lust-envy, lust-gluttony, lust-wantonness; hence the Apostle speaketh of serving divers lusts; the man or woman that is drawn away with these lusts, he is the servant, and the lust is the Master, (<hi>Tit.</hi> 3.3.) but saith the Apostle, We serve the Lord Christ; and if ye be Christs servants, then you are heirs. In this world you may be a mans servant, and yet not be his heir; but if you be Christs servants, you are Christs heirs.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Christs house; the Saints are Christs house, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6. and although wicked men say they love the House of God, meaning a place of Lime and stones; yet they love not the true house of God, where he dwelleth, which is the Saints, who are the habitations of God through the Spirit, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.22. of whom God saith, He will dwell in them and walk in them. Now if ye be of Christs house, of this houshold of Faith, of Christs family, then are ye heirs.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:119986:52"/>
            <p>The second thing, Why all divine priviledges, Heaven and happiness, belong to them that are Christs, and why not to them that are of the Law. First, Why they belong to the one. Secondly, Why they belong not to the other.</p>
            <p>For the first, Why they belong to the one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reason.</hi> 1. Because the Lord Jesus hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased all divine priviledges, Heaven and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness for his; therefore Heaven is called the purchased possession; Christ hath purchased re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of sins, faith and eternal life for them, which in the appointed season they shal receive. Fathers lay up for their own children, though not for others, husbands provide for their own wives, though not for others; the Lord Jesus hath purchased an inheritance undefiled, which fadeth not away, reserved in Heaven for his children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reas.</hi> 2. Because Christ is theirs; he that hath the son, hath life; all divine priviledges, life and glory must needs belong to them that have the son, that have union with Christ, that have him dwelling in their hearts by Faith; no Christ, no Heaven; no Christ, no happiness, no Glory, no inheritance among those that are sanctified by faith that is in him; but if you be Christs, and Christ yours, yours is the kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reas.</hi> 3. Because we are the children of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119986:52"/>God by Faith in Jesus Christ, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. and if children, then we must needs be heirs. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Why divine priviledges, Heaven and happiness, do not belong to them that are of the Law, seeing that they may do so many good works for the matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reas.</hi> 1. Because that there is no way of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heirs, but according to the promise, as you have it in the Text; and <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.18. saith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, <hi>If the inheritance be of the Law, its no more of promise;</hi> as if the Apostle had said, If it be of the Law and works, it cannot be of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, and the promise; but saith he, God gave it to <hi>Abraham</hi> by promise; therefore saith the Apostle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.28. we as <hi>Isaac</hi> was, are the children of the promise; We, that is to say, we that are heirs, and co-heirs with Christ; and in the same chapter saith he, <hi>Abraham</hi> had two sons, the one born of a bond woman, the other of a free-woman: now he that was born of the bond-woman was after the flesh; but he that was born of the free woman was by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise. And at the last verse saith he, Cast out the bond-woman and her son; for the son of the bond woman shall not be heir with the son of the free-woman; No, he must not be heir, he cannot be heir, because there is no other way of being heirs but according to the promise, that is to say, according to the promise of life in
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119986:53"/>Christ Jesus; and therefore if there be never such alteration in men, never so much Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be they never so strict in their conversati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, framing themselves never so much accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law, yet this will not make them heirs; that must be freely, and onely by grace; if ye be heirs, ye must be children of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reas.</hi> 2. Because the Law cannot give life; saith the Apostle, <hi>(Gal.</hi> 3.21.) If there had been a Law given that could have given life, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily righteousness had been by the Law; but there is no Law that can give life, but the Law of life in Christ Jesus, which maketh us free from the Law of sin and death; the Law of <hi>Moses</hi> is called the Law of death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reas.</hi> 3. Those that are of the Law cannot be heirs, because as the Apostle saith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. <hi>as many as are of the Law, are under the curse;</hi> They are so far from being heirs of life and glory, that notwithstanding all their obedience and conformity to the Law, yet they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the curse; for saith the Apostle, its written, Cursed is every one that continueth not in every thing that is written in the Book of the Law to do it: so that to those that are under the Law, the Law saith, Man or woman, thou art accursed because thou hast not done every thing that I require, and if thou hast failed in one point, thou art guilty of all; O therefore, in what a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119986:53"/>miserare condition are those that have not the Lord Jesus as a City of refuge to flie unto, and so to make answer unto the Law and say, O Law, indeed I have nor continued in every thing that thou requirest; and yet I am not accursed; for my dear Saviour hath taken away thy curse from me, by being made a curse for me; by whom I am as righteous before God as if I had never sinned, he being made of God unto me Wisdom, righteousness, sanctification and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.) And the Prophet <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saiah</hi> speaking of those that are Christs, saith he, Surely shall one say In the Lord have I righteousness and strength; unto him shall men come, and in him shall all the house of Israel be justified, and shall glory, (<hi>Isa.</hi> 45. <hi>ult</hi>) Those that are of the Law, comfort themselves and say, Surely there is a great change in my life, and surely I have abundance of righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in my self; but do those that are Christs, fetch their comfort and their hope of glory from their observance of the Law, and their own Righteousness? No, but surely shall one, every one that is Christs, say, In the Lord have I righteousness; in my self I am a sinful creature, but in the Lord Jesus have I righteousness; he is the Lord my righteousness; and it followeth, In him shall all the house of Israel be justified; Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified in him, not by the Law, but as the Apostle saith, By him whosoever believeth, shall be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:119986:54"/>from all that he could not be justified from by the Law of <hi>Moses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third is, To shew you the great happiness and glorious priviledges of those that are Christs.</p>
            <p n="1">I. If ye be Christs seed, and Christs chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You shall endure for ever; <hi>David</hi> speaking of Christ, saith, His seed shall endure for ever, (<hi>Psal.</hi> 89.29.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. Christs seed and children are never left and forsaken of God, which is a glorious privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge indeed, that the great God of Heaven and earth will never leave them nor forsake them; in the same Psalm saith <hi>David,</hi> If his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that is Christs children, forsake my Law, and walk not in my judgements, if they break my Statutes, and keep not my commandments, then will I visit their iniquity; <hi>Nevertheless my lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindness will I not utterly take away, nor suffer my faithfulness to faile,</hi> (<hi>Psal.</hi> 89.30, 31, 32, 33.) Now what a blessed condition are Christs children in? when they sin, the Lord will visit their transgression with a rod; he will for their good chasten them; but yet his loving-kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness he will not utterly take away; still God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth them as well as ever, and he will not cast them off, he will not forsake them; the Lord Christ doth not carry himself to his children as the ship Carpenter doth with the ship; when
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119986:54"/>once he hath built it, he puts it unto the Sea, and leaveth it to the storms, and tempests, and rocks; and he leaveth it and looketh no more after it; I say the Lord doth not thus with those that are his; he doth not give them faith and knowledge of himself, and so leave the soul to the assaults and fiery darts of the devil, and the corruption of his own heart: but the Lord himself is in the ship, and he will not leave nor forsake the poor soul, but will be his guide even unto death: he will be the Pilot in the ship, that wil secure the ship in all storms and tempests; for the winds and the sea obey him; and he will keep it out of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the rocks, and by the gales of his spirit, the ship of the believers soul shall sail safely; till it arrive at the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the promised Land, of which its an heir, by being one of the children of the King of Glory, the Lord Jesus.</p>
            <p n="2">II. If ye be Christs brethren also, ye are in a blessed condition; for</p>
            <p n="1">1. To have him who is God equal with the Father, <hi>the fellow of the Lord of Hosts,</hi> to be our brother, must needs be a great priviledge; to have one of the Angels to be our brother, were a high priviledge; but to have the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, in whom dwelleth the fulness of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head bodily, to have such a neer relation unto him, is a high priviledge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To have him who was sent to seek and to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119986:55"/>save that which was lost, to have him for our brother, then to be sure we shall be sought out, and be saved by him; what a priviledge is this?</p>
            <p n="3">3. To have him for our Brother who hath all things put into his hand, who hath all power given him in heaven and in earth, this must needs be a great priviledge; as now, when <hi>Jacobs</hi> sons went to buy corn in <hi>Egypt,</hi> what a great privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge was it that they had a Brother <hi>Joseph,</hi> that was great in the land, that had the disposing of all things? so its with Jesus Christ; the Father hath put the mannagement of all things into his hands, he is the Judge of the quick and the dead; and that he should be your Brother! But at present its with some of Christs brethren as it was with <hi>Josephs</hi> Brethren; a great while they did not know that <hi>Joseph</hi> was their Brother, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he manifested himself to them; and in that day when the Lord Jesus shall manifest himself to you and say, I am your Brother, you are in that neer and dear relation unto me, to be my brethren, O then this will appear wonderful to you; and it may be in allusion unto <hi>Josephs</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifesting himself and his name unto his Brethren doth the Lord Iesus our spiritual <hi>Joseph</hi> say, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.11. I will manifest my name unto my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; what joy will there be in the hearts of Christs Brethren in that day?</p>
            <p n="3">III. If you be Christs Spouses, then also you
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119986:55"/>have many glorious Priviledges, As</p>
            <p n="1">1. All Suits are comment't against the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; if a woman be never so much in debt, yet when once she is married, she cannot be sued; but her husband, he must answer for all her debts; so if thou beest Christs spouse, married to him, though thou owest never so much, and the Law come and accuse, yet thou maist say, Go to my husband Christ, and he will answer for me.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It must needs be a glorious priviledge to be Christs Spouse, because Christ maketh his Spouse a great Ioynture; the poorest Saint hath a greater joynture then ten thousand worlds; he hath heaven that glorious inheritance. You think many Kings and Noblemen make their wives great Ioyntures; O nothing to the Ioynture that the Lord Iesus maketh his Spouses.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You have the heir of all things for your husband, Christs Spouses have not a poor hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, but one that is heir of all things; now when the husband is rich, the wife is rich; she hath an interest in her husbands riches; so hath the spouse of Christ; she is rich in the riches of Christ.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Spouses of Christ have a great por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the Lord himself is their portion, who is an everlasting portion; other portions may be spent, but the Lord is an everlasting por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:119986:56"/>5. They that are Christs Spouses have the fairest of ten thousand for their husband; the Spouse in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> saith of the Lord Iesus, her Husband, His countenance is most sweet, yea he is altogether lovely, this is my beloved, and this is my friend, one that is fairer then the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men; he hath grace poured into his lips. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10, 16. <hi>Psal.</hi> 45.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They that are Christs Spouses, have a husband that hath dear love and affections to them; when a woman is married, if she have a dear and loving husband, she accounts it a great happiness, and it maketh that relation very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable. If you be Christs, if you be his Spou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, you have a husband whose love is infinitely beyond the love of all the husbands in the world; therefore saith the Apostle, <hi>Husbands, love your wives, as Christ also loved his Church, and gave himself for it, (Eph.</hi> 5.25.) And in another place, <hi>Who loved me, and gave himself for me;</hi> In this world many marry upon slender grounds of love, but all Christs Spouses have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite testimony of his love; the Spouse of Christ cannot say A bloody husband thou hast been to me, but rather may the Lord Christ say, A bloody wife hast thou been to me; it cost me the warmest blood in my heart to deliver thee from wrath to come; if there should be a poor woman very unhandsome, much in debt, and a Kings son should come and pay all her debts,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119986:56"/>and marry her, he would express abundance of love to that woman; yet this would be short of Christs love. The Lord Jesus doth not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for portion, as most of the sons of men do; but he marrieth poor beggars, poor and blind, and naked, that have not a wedding garment till he put it on; neither doth the Lord Jesus marry for beauty, as many of the children of men do; but the Fairest of ten thousand marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth poor blackamoors; here's pure love; thus Christs Spouses have large testimony of Christs infinite love, which is a great priviledge.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If ye be Christs Church, then you have glorious priviledges by it; also you shall have them set down in the <hi>Ephesians. Eph</hi> 5.23.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You have Christ to be your head; Christ he is the head of the Church, your head is in Heaven.</p>
            <p>The head is the seat of care, and contriveth for the good of the body, (<hi>Eph.</hi> 5.23.) so the Church of Christ; they may-cast their care upon the Lord Christ their head, for he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for them; the father hath not left the good of his people to the care of Angels, but hath trusted Jesus Christ with it, who is their head.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you be Christs Church, the Lord Jesus, the Apostle saith, will sanctifie you and cleanse you with the washing of water by the word, and present you to himself <hi>a glorious Church, not having spot or wrinckle, or any such thing, but
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119986:57"/>holy and without blemish, (Eph.</hi> 5.26, 27.) and is not this a great priviledge, not to be left in your sins, but to be sanctified in Christ Jesus, and to be made holy as he is holy?</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Lord Jesus is dear over his Church; hence saith the Apostle, no man ever yet hated his own flesh, but loveth it and cherisheth it, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as the Lord the Church; the Lord Iesus che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risheth his Church in his bosome, he carrieth them in his bosome, and is dear over them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.29.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If ye be Christs shep, then</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Priviledge</hi> 1. Iesus Christ knoweth you; saith Christ, I am the good shepheard that know my sheep, and I am known of mine, (<hi>Joh.</hi> 10.17.) though one that is Christs, be never so poor, live in never such a by-corner, yet the son of God and the Angels of Heaven know him, and have communion and acquaintance with him, and he with them; though the great ones of the world take no notice of thee, yet the son of God doth, and knoweth thee by name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Priv</hi> 2. Iesus Christ giveth them eternal life; My sheep saith Christ, hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me, and I give unto them eternal life, and they shall never perish, neither shall any man be able to pluck them out of my hands (<hi>Joh.</hi> 10.27, 28,) Here's a glorious priviledge, that though so many pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish and die in their sins, yet you shall never pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish;
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119986:57"/>when the Goats shall be set on the left hand, and Christ shall say unto them, Go ye cursed into everlasting hell fire, (<hi>Matth.</hi> 25.) then you that are Christs, you that are his sheep, shall be set on his right hand, and he will say unto you, <hi>Come ye blessed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the beginning of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Priv.</hi> 3. You that are Christs sheep, have an excellent shepheard; the Lord Iesus therefore is called the great shepheard of the sheep, (<hi>Heb.</hi> 13.) and saith the Prophet <hi>Isaiah,</hi> He shall feed his flock like a shepheard, he shall gather the Lambs in his arms, and shall gently lead them that are with young, (<hi>Isa</hi> 45.11.) the poor weak Lambs of Christ shall be carried in his arms and bosom; he will be tender over you.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If ye be Christs, if you be his servants, that ye serve the Lord Christ, you have many glorious priviledges; for</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Priv.</hi> 1. His service is perfect freedom, the service of Christ is no bondage nor slavery; his commandments are not grievous, but his yoak is easie and his burden is light, (<hi>Matth.</hi> 11. <hi>ult.</hi>) that soul that is Christs servant, is guided by the royal law of liberty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Priv.</hi> 2. Where Iesus Christ the blessed Lord of life is, there shall they be to all eternity, as Christ saith, Where I am, there shall also my
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119986:58"/>servant be, (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.26.) and what a great priviledge is this to be where Christ is, to behold his glory? that when the servants of the devil shall be in the bottomless pit with him, the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Christ shall be where he is, in whose presence there is fulness of joy, and at whose right hand there are pleasures for evermore; and saith the Lord (<hi>Isa</hi> 65.13.) <hi>Behold my ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants shall eat, but ye shall be hungry; my ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants shall drink, but ye shall be thirsty; behold my servants shall rejoyce, but ye shall be ashamed.</hi> Mark, my servants shall drink, that is to say, I have an everlasting banquet for them when they shall have a feast of fat things, of Wine on the Lees well refined, when I will say, eat O friends, yea drink abundantly, O my beloved! but saith he, Ye shall be thirsty, ye shall lie in the flames of devouring fire, and as it was with <hi>Dives,</hi> ye shall cry for one drop of water to cool your tongues; and it followeth, Behold my servants shall sing for joy of heart, but ye shall cry for sorrow of heart, and shall howle for vexation of Spirit; as if he had said, When my servants shall be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in Heaven, and see their names written in the book of life, then shall the world of the ungodly lie howling in utter darkness, where is weeping and wailing, and gnashing of teeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Priv.</hi> 3. Christs servants have the great God of heaven and earth to honour them, this is a glorious priviledge, Christ himself said it, <hi>If any
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119986:58"/>man serve me, him will my Father honour, (Ioh.</hi> 12.26.) as he said, What shall be done to the man whom the King will honour? but then what shall be done to the man whom the great God of Heaven will honour? God will honour his servants unto all eternity, though the world despise them, yet he will honour them for ever to spend eternity with him; yea he honoureth them in this world. You would think it a great honour to you, if some Nobleman or Knight should come to your houses, and be with you a few days; why; the great God dwelleth with his people, and taketh up his abode with them; O what an honour is this!</p>
            <p n="7">7. They that are Christs people, have many glorious priviledges, as</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Priv.</hi> 1. They are a blessed people; Blessed saith <hi>David,</hi> are the people that are in such a a case, who have the Lord for their God; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the men of the world look upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iesus as the off scouring of all things, yet they are blessed men and women, and would not change their condition with the greatest Emperour in the world that is none of Christs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Priv.</hi> 2. Christs people are saved from their sins, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.21. <hi>He shall save his people from their sins,</hi> saith that Scripture, that though they have committed as many sins as they have hairs on their heads, which cannot be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:119986:59"/>yet the blood of Iesus cleanseth them from all their sins, they are saved from all their sins; now saith <hi>David,</hi> blessed is the man whose iniquity is pardoned, whose sin is covered, (<hi>Psal.</hi> 32.1.) what a happy condition are the people of Iesus in, that though their iniquities be sought for, they cannot be found? for the Lord Iesus our Scape-Goat hath carried them into the land of forgetfulness; and <hi>Psal.</hi> 85.2. <hi>Thou hast forgiven the iniquity of thy people, and thou hast covered all their sins;</hi> not one sin, but all their sins; and <hi>Isa.</hi> 40.1, 2. Comfort ye, comfort ye my people saith God, speak comfortably unto <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> say unto her that her iniquity is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Priv.</hi> 3. They have the blessing of Heaven upon them; saith <hi>David, Thy blessing is upon thy people, (Psal.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi>) though they do not enjoy so much of the world as others do; yet that which is better then ten thousand worlds, they have the blessing of God upon them, they have the blessing of God upon their souls, they have the blessings out of Sion, those spiritual blessings in heavenly things in Christ, and they have the blessing of God, and taste the love of God in that little they enjoy of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Priv.</hi> 4. The Lord will speak peace to his people; saith <hi>David,</hi> I will hear what the Lord will say, for <hi>he will speak peace to his people, and to his Saints, (Psal.</hi> 85.8.) What a blessed thing
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119986:59"/>is this, when the Law and our own Consciences tell us we have committed a thousand sins, and the wages of sin is death, that now the Lord speaketh peace and saith, I am thy salvation? the people of Jesus onely have that peace of God which passeth all understanding, that even when they are most sensible of their own vileness and sinfulness, and see themselves to be the greatest of sinners, that yet even then I say, they have joy and peace in believing; those that are of the Law say to their duties and performances and good works, ye are our peace; but say the people of Jesus, The Lord Christ he is our peace: and they have peace spoken to their consciences by the blood of Jesus, as <hi>David</hi> saith, The Lord will bless his people with peace; the Lord bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth many of the world with riches, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and children; but he blesseth his people with peace, with the injoyment of himself, with peace of Conscience and joy in the Holy Ghost, <hi>Psal.</hi> 29.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Priv.</hi> 5. They are Christs favourites; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore saith <hi>David, Remember me with that favour thou bearest to thy own people, (Psal.</hi> 106.4.) O thats a great favour. You think that they are happy men that are favourites of the Kings and great ones of the world; Nay, but the poorest Saint, though he be despised in the world, yet he is one of the God of Heavens favourites; and what a blessed thing is this? if you be Christs
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:119986:60"/>people, you are Christs favourites. You think what a great happiness it were if you were in such a ones favour and love; alas, you may be in their favour and love to day, &amp; out to morrow; but the Lord loveth with an everlasting love; once in his favour, ever in his favour; once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of him, and ever beloved of him. (<hi>Jer.</hi> 31.3.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Priv.</hi> 5. The Lord will never leave them nor forsake them. <hi>Psal.</hi> 94.14. <hi>The Lord will not cast off his people;</hi> you that are Christs peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, though you have so many weaknesses and corruptions, yet here is matter of everlasting consolation to you, the Lord will not cast off his people; and is not this a glorious privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?</p>
            <p n="8">8. If ye be Christs, the <hi>exceeding large and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promises</hi> of the Gospel belong to you; the promises of the Gospel all are Yea and Amen, in Christ, to all that are his. It were a glorious priviledge to have interest in one of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises; but to have interest in all the promises, is very glorious, as in that promise, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. I will write my Laws in their hearts, and put my fear in their hearts, and they shall never depart from me; and that in <hi>Ezech.</hi> 36. A new heart also will I give you, and a new spirit will I put within you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Hos.</hi> 14.4. I will heal their back-slidings; and <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. towards the end, I will be mercisul
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119986:60"/>unto their unrighteousness, and I will remember their fins no more. Those that are Christs, are rich in the promise, though they be poor in possession.</p>
            <p n="9">9. If ye be Christs, you are <hi>Abrahams</hi> seed; though ye are not circumcised as he was, yet you are of the spiritual seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who saw Christs day afar off, and was glad.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Heirs according to the promise, <hi>heirs of the grace of life;</hi> you shall be made <hi>partakers of the inheritancs of the Saints in light,</hi> though some of you now be Saints in darkness, yet you shall one day be Saints in light; though you now <hi>walk in darkness and see no light;</hi> yet the Lord will be your everlasting light, and ere long the days of your mourning shall be ended, and all tears wiped from your eys; though these heirs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the promise at present, are cut short, yet they shall shortly enjoy that inheritance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible and undefiled, which fadeth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; its reserved in Heaven for them.</p>
            <p n="11">11. In a word, to let you see that the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of those that are Christs, is very great, let me direct you to that of the Apostle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22.23. All are yours, and ye are Christs, and Christ is Gods; <hi>all are yours if you be Christs,</hi> whither <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Apollos,</hi> saith the Apostle; all the gifts that Iesus Christ hath given to men, are for your edification and consolation; and not onely mens gifts, but saith the Apostle, the world too, O ye
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:119986:61"/>sons and daughters of Sion, the world is yours, though you enjoy so little of it; but if the Lord saw it good for you, there is nothing in the whole world but you should have it; and things present, and things to come, all are yours; there is much in those words, things to come; that holdeth out Heavens glory and all the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments there; and though Saints are at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent cut short, yet they may ground upon this, that the Lord will do them that good that is most for their good.</p>
            <p>The fourth thing; you have shown us the great happiness and glorious priviledge; O but how shall we know whither we are Christs.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Would you know whither you are Christs seed and Christs children?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Are you of those that honour the Lord Iesus in your hearts, and in your lives; <hi>If I be a father, where is my honour?</hi> if you be the children of that Antient of days, you will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him I say in your hearts and in your lives.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you be the children of Christ, you can approve of him and his ways; Christ saith, Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that is himself, is justified of her children; though the world speak ill of Christ and his blessed ways, yet wisdoms children will justifie him and his wayes, that his wayes are wayes of pleasantness, and all his paths are peace, that as the Martyr said, None but Christ, none but Christ, and as <hi>David</hi> said of <hi>Goliahs</hi> sword,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119986:61"/>there is none to that, so saith a believer, there is none to Christ; whom have I in Heaven but thee, and whom do I desire on earth besides thee?</p>
            <p n="2">II. Would you know whether you are Christs brethren? the Lord Iesus tells us who are his brethren, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.50. <hi>He that doth the will of my father, he is my brother and sister;</hi> you <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> that delight to do the will of God, the will of God goeth far; this is the will of God, that you should believe on his son Iesus Christ, and love one another; and again in another place saith the Apostle, This is the will of God, even your sanctification. Now they that do the will of God aright, do the will of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it's the will of God; they do not pray, hear, give to the poor, thinking to make a lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Heaven of their own works; but saith one that is Christs, I pray, hear, give to the poor, because this is the will of my God concerning me, who hath created me in Christ Iesus unto good works which God before ordained that I should walk in them; and because I am saved freely by his Grace, therefore I desire to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in every good work to do his will.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Would you know whether you are Christs people, and have those glorious privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges belonging to you, that belong to those that are Christs people?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Christs people are a peculiar people; the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:119986:62"/>
               <hi>Lord Jesus hath purchased them to himself to be a peculiar people,</hi> (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14.) As it was said of <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joshua,</hi> that they were men of another spirit, its true of all the people of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, they are men and women of another spirit then is in the world; as the Apostle saith in the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> We, faith he, have not received the spirit of the world, but the spirit which is of God; thus are they a peculiar people; they have a peculiar spirit, which in the Scripture is called a new spirit; the people of Jesus have peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar experiences, peculiar hopes, peculiar aims, peculiar desires, peculiar language.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A holy people; therefore they are called the people of his holiness; the Lord Jesus will not suffer his people to walk in the vanity of their minds, and to have their conversation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the course of this world, but he traineth them up in mortification and holiness, till they come to be holy as he is holy, and the Lord Christ doth make sin so hateful to them that are his, that they desire as well that their sins may die as that their souls may live; they desire as well that their sins may be destroyed as that their souls may be saved.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If you be Christs people, you will be a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling people, <hi>Psal.</hi> 110.3. Thy people shall be a willing people in the day of thy power; though before they would not come to Christ that they might have life, yet when the day of Christs
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:119986:62"/>power cometh, then they are made of unwilling, willing; though <hi>Paul</hi> was such an enemy to Christ a great while, yet when the day of Christs power cometh, then he is willing; Lord, saith he, what wilt thou have me to do? as if he had said, Now thou hast conquered my will, and made me now willing to believe, to be obedient to thee; If you belong to Christ, you that are most averse to Christ, and say he shall not reign over you, yet you shall by the power of Christ be made willing to have Christ for your onely Saviour and King, to rule in your hearts; you will be willing to sell all to buy that pearl of great price, and count all things but loss and dung, that you may win Christ, and be found in him; you will be willing to have all your lusts subdued and destroyed.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Would you know whether you are Christs Spouses?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Christs Spouses have precious thoughts of Christ, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10, 14. You shall see what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious thoughts of Christ the Spouse had; saith she, <hi>He is white and ruddy, the fairest of ten thousand;</hi> you that have low thoughts of Christ, and see no beauty in him wherefore you should desire him, you are not yet married to Christ, you have not yet lien in the bosome of the Lord Jesus.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you be Christs Spouses, you have dear love and affections unto Christ. O what dear
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:119986:63"/>love to Christ had the Spouse! saith she, thy love is better then wine; and because of the savour of thy oyntments, thy name is as oyntment powred forth, therefore do the virgins lovethee; the Spouses of Christ love him not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the good they have by him, but they see that excellency in Christ, and personall beauty in him, that though they should never be the better for Christ, yet they could not but love him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Christs Spouses love the presence of Christ much, as a good wife loveth to have her husband at home with her; she could be content to fare hardly, go meanly, that she might but enjoy her husbands company; so 'tis with the Spouses of Christ; they could be content not to have in this world whereon to lay their heads, so they might but enjoy more of Christs presence, as <hi>Luther</hi> said, I had rather be in Hell with Christ, then in Heaven without him; a Spouse of Christ had rather be in poverty with Christ, then in riches without him; had rather be in disgrace with Christ, then to be in honour without him; as the same <hi>Luther</hi> said sweetly, I had rather fall with Christ then stand with <hi>Caesar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Christs Spouses are subject unto Christ, as <hi>Sarah</hi> was subject unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> obeyed him and called him Lord; therefore saith the Apostle, as the Church is subject unto Christ, so let wives be to their own husbands.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:119986:63"/>V. Would you know whether you are Christs sheep?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Christs sheep know him. I, saith Christ, know my sheep, and am known of mine, (<hi>Joh.</hi> 10.16.) You that have no knowledge of Christ, that know no more of Christ then you do what's done now in the farthest part of the world, can you say you are Christs sheep? and when the Lord Jesus saith, He is known of his sheep, his sheep have not meerly a head, but a heart-knowledge of Christ, not a notional, but an experimental knowledge of Christ; not an informing onely, but a transforming knowledge of him; they have an experimental knowledge of him and the power of his Resurrection, and the fellowship of his sufferings, being made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable unto his death.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Christs sheep hear his voice, as Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self saith, My sheep hear my voice, and I know them, (<hi>Joh.</hi> 10.27.) you cannot know aright that you are Christs sheep, unless you have heard his voice behind you, saying, This is the way, walk in it, (<hi>Isa.</hi> 30.20, 21.) the Lord Jesus cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out to the soul that is walking in the broad way that leadeth to destruction, and saith, Thou art out of the way; he showeth the soul that the path of prophaness is not the path of life; but the spirit convinceth the soul of sin, and that the end of that path will be death and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine to the soul; and then whereas the soul would
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:119986:64"/>then think that if he reform and amend his life, he might be happy: no saith that voice, that will not do it, but this is the way; I, saith the voice, am the way, the truth, and the life; no man cometh to the Father but by me.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If you be Christs sheep, you are followers of Christ, as the Lord Jesus saith, My sheep hear my voyce, and I know them, and they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me, (<hi>Joh.</hi> 10.27.) The poor Saints that hear the sweet voice and calls of Christ, cannot choose but follow him; therefore when the Lord Jesus calleth us out of darkness into his marveilous light, he taketh off that load of sin that lay upon our shoulders, opens the prison door, and saith, Follow me; The believer saith to Christ as <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>th</hi> said to <hi>Orphah,</hi> where thou go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, I will go, where thou lodgest I will lodge, where thou diest I will die; (<hi>Ruth.</hi> 1.16, 17.) and as <hi>Peter</hi> to Christ, Lord, whither should I go? thou onely hast the words of eternal life; what should I go from thee to <hi>Moses?</hi> O no, my sweet Saviour! Should I go from thee to the world? O no, my sweet Saviour; thou onely art able to justifie me, save me to the utmost; thou onely art able to comfort me, strengthen me, and make glad my heart.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Would you know whither you are Christs servants?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then you obey the Lord Jesus; his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants you are to whom you obey, whither of sin
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:119986:64"/>unto death, or of the Lord Jesus unto eternal life; O consider, whom do you obey in the whole course of your lives, God or men; Christ or <hi>Belial;</hi> for his servants you are, to whom ye obey; therefore saith Christ, why call ye me Lord, Lord, and do not the things which I say, as if he had said, Its in vain so to do; how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you are common swearers, yet you will call Christ Lord, and profess to be his servants; but its in vain; why do not you do the things which he saith, if you be his servants? he saith, Swear not at all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you be Christs servants, you are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in his work, as the Apostle said, for me to live is Christ; you live to do Christs work and business in the world; you see and know you are not your own, but Christs; and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire as you live by Christ, so to live to Christ and for Christ, as well as hereafter with Christ.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Would you know whether you be Christs? if you be Christs, sin hath not domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over you; <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24. They that are Christs, have crucifyed the flesh with the affections and lusts; sin cannot have dominion where its cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and its crucified in all that are Christs; its with sin in those that are Christs, as it was with those beasts we read of in <hi>Daniel;</hi> their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion is taken away though their lives be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed for a season, though some corruption remains, yet none raigns.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:119986:65"/>VIII. Those that are Christs, bear something of his image and likeness, as Christ said to the Pharisees, Whose image and superscription is this? <hi>Caesars</hi> say they, then saith Christ, give unto <hi>Caesar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caesars,</hi> and to God the things that are Gods: O consider whether you have Christs image stampt upon you.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. If you be Christs, his children, brethren, spouses, people, as we have shown, I say then you wil rejoyce more that you are Christs, then if you had ten thousand worlds; it was the Spouses song, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2, 16. My beloved, that is, Christ, is mine and I am his, I count my self saith a Saint, more happy that I can say Christ is mine then if I could say all the world is mine; and that I am Christs, is a comfort to me in all conditions, temptations, afflictions.</p>
            <p n="10">X. Would you know whether you be Christs? You may certainly know it by this. If you be Christs, you have the spirit of Christ <hi>Rom</hi> 8.9. <hi>He that hath not the spirit of Christ, is none of his,</hi> and I pray mark what I say in the name of the Lord this day to you that mock and jeer at the Spirit, and tell the Saints in scorn and derision that they pray by the Spirit, and speak by the spirit: why what will become of you, and what do you think of your selves, if you have not the Spirit of Christ? the Apostle saith, you are none of his. Go home therefore and consider,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:119986:65"/>What have I done in reproaching men for pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and prophecying in the Spirit? if I my self have not the Spirit of Christ, I am none of his; and you that mock so at the Spirit, do you think you have yet received the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaere.</hi> But how shall I know whither I have the Spirit of Christ?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. If thou hast the Spirit of Christ, thou art throughly convinc't of sin by that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; for that Spirit convinceth of sin; O thou that hast the Spirit of Christ, hast not thou been convinc't of thy own sinfulness and wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and saw thy great need of Christ, and thy undone condition without him? therefore you that see not your undone condition without Christ, that you are lost if you be not found in him, you have not the Spirit, (<hi>Joh.</hi> 16.9.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. If thou hast the Spirit of Christ, thou seest thine own right to be but menstruous rags, and that the Lord Christ is the Lord our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, (<hi>Joh.</hi> 16.9.) Therefore thou that art of the Law, and goest about to establish thy own right, and dost not submit to the righteousness of God by saith, thou hast not this Spirit of Christ: for as he saith, That Spirit shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of righteousness, that is to say, shall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent his righteousnes, as that which is the onely righteousness.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If thou hast the Spirit of Christ, thou art sanctified; (<hi>Rom.</hi> 15.16.) therefore the Spirit
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:119986:66"/>of Christ is called the spirit of holiness, and the spirit of judgement and of burning: it burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up the thorns of the flesh; and therefore holiness is set out in the Scripture by walking in the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If thou hast the spirit of Christ, thou art acquainted with the Lord Jesus, by that Spirit. as Christ saith; My spirit shall take of mine, and shew it unto you; the spirit taketh Christs love, and sheweth it unto us: it taketh of Christs beauty &amp; sheweth it unto us; it taketh of Christs fulness, and sheweth unto us. And thus those that have the Spirit of Christ come to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with Christ.</p>
            <p>Now of all the ways to know whether we are Christs, we may say of this last as <hi>David</hi> said of <hi>Goliahs</hi> sword, There is none to that.</p>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>Ʋse.</hi> 1.</head>
               <p>Do so many glorious Priviledges as we have shown, belong to them that are Christs? O then, by all those characters we have given you, examine whether you be Christs. The Apostle doth not say, If you be professors, then are you <hi>Abrahams</hi> seed, and heirs according to the promise: neither doth he say that those that are of such a judgement, are the heirs; but saith, if ye be Christs, if ye be his children, if ye be his Spouses, his brethren, his people, then are you the children of faithful <hi>Abraham,</hi> and heirs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the promise; and if you examine, it
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:119986:66"/>may be instead of being Christs, you will find that you have been the devils, and your own, and the worlds all your days, and not Christs: and though you enjoy so much honour, riches and pleasures in the world, and with <hi>Dives</hi> fare deliciously every day, if this did but sink into your hearts to consider that you are none of Christs, this would cast a damp upon all your jollity in this world: yea, if there were no Hell, you would be miserable in that you are none of Christs, in that you belong not to the Lord of Glory; and upon examining by those rules that we have set down, some of you may finde, that instead of being Christs children, you have been the devils children; as Christ told the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sees,</hi> saith he, Ye are of your father the Devil, and his works you do: and instead of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Christs servants, you are the devils servants, and do his will, and not Christs; and do his works, and not Christs: may not the Lord say to many of you, as <hi>Psal.</hi> 95. that you are a people that do erre in your hearts, and have not known his wayes? as the Apostle complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, The way of peace, which is Christ, they they have not known; you have known the devils ways: O but did you ever yet know the ways of Christ, whose wayes are wayes of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>santness, and all his paths are peace; I beseech you consider these things, and the Lord let you see the condition that you are in; and O that the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:119986:67"/>Lord would pluck you as firebrands out of the fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>Ʋse.</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>Is it so, that all divine priviledges, Heaven and happiness, belong to them that are Christs, and to them onely; then this Doctrine I know will greatly offend those that are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally prophane, and those who are of the Law, that notwithstanding all their good meanings and performances, they shall not be heirs; but you will certainly finde it true another day; and O that now you might no longer build upon the sands of your own Righteousness, but that you may be set upon that Rock that is higher then you, that you may build upon that Rock of ages, that glorious and sure foundation the Lord Jesus; but do you think by your good meanings and broken performances, to be heirs of the kingdom? what did the Lord Jesus say to the Pharisees? publicans, and harlots shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the kingdom or God before you: I know this will grievously offend you, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense you; and indeed as <hi>Luther</hi> said, to preach the Gospel aright, is the way for a man to bring upon himself the fury and madness of the world; but saith he, if the world should not be offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with me, I should be offended with the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>Ʋse</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>Of advice and counsel to them that are Christs. O you that are Christs children, be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient children unto him, and do not you scrape
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:119986:67"/>for your selves in the world; you have a Father that knoweth your wants, that will provide for you; O do not set you affections on things below, you are heirs of glory, you have in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven an enduring substance; you that are Christs Spouses, be subject to him in every thing; if ye be Christs sheep follow him; if ye be Christs servants, do the things which he saith; Lay out your selves wholly for Christ, you are not your own. If ye be Christs house, let the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus rule in you; we shewed you that the Saints were Christs house; now as it was decreed by that King, <hi>Esth.</hi> 1. <hi>ult.</hi> that every man should bear rule in his own house; O let not the devil bear rule, nor any lust bear rule in you, but let Christ bear rule in his own house; ye are Christs, his own; house and is it not lawful for a man to do what he will with his own? saith Christ. O be you willing to be at Christs dispose in every thing, and let Christ do what he will with you and in you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>Ʋse</hi> 4.</head>
               <p>By all that hath been said, I hope you that have been hitherto enemies of Christ, opposers of him and his wayes, that even you are now willing to be Christs, and say, O that I may be Christs! the Lord Jesus giveth you incouragement saying, Whosoever cometh to me, I will in no wise cast out; whatsoever thou art, come to Christ and thou shalt be welcome; the arms of Christ
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:119986:68"/>are wide open to receive poor sinners; and what happy men and women will you be, if you be Christs; and why may you not yet be Christs, and so <hi>Abrahams</hi> seed, and heirs according to the promise? as the Lord Jesus said, God is able of these stones to raise up children unto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham;</hi> though at present you have never such sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hearts, yet the Lord is able to break your stony flinty hearts, upon the soft pillow of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace; and so to make you Christs his children, and so the children of faithful <hi>Abraham;</hi> and though you are not yet Christs people, yet what saith the Lord? I have called them my people which were not my people; O that these dry bones may live; O that your eys might be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the god of this world might no longer blinde your eyes, but that the light of the glory of God, that shineth in the face of Jesus Christ, might shine into your hearts.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:119986:68"/>
            <head>ELECTION Before the FOVNDATION of the WORLD.</head>
            <head type="sub">Sermon II.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Act. 13.48.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And when the Gentiles heard this, they were glad and glorified the Word of the Lord, and as many as were ordained to eternal life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>YOu have in this chapter, <hi>Paul</hi> preaching forgiveness of sins by Jesus Christ, assuring the people, that whosoever believe on him shall be justified from all that they could not be justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Law of <hi>Moses;</hi> all that believe,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:119986:69"/>Jew and Gentile; here he holdeth forth the righteousness of God, which is by faith of Jesus Christ to be unto all and upon all them that believe, and sheweth them that Christ is set to be a light of the Gentiles, that he should be for salvation to the ends of the earth; now many of the Jews spake against those things which were spoken by <hi>Paul,</hi> contradicting and blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming, and put away this Doctrine of Grace; but when the Gentiles heard this, they glorifyed the word of the Lord; and though so many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spised, rejected, and set Christ at naught, yet saith he, as many as were ordained to eternal life believed; those among them that belonged to the election of Grace, the Lord gave them Faith, overcame their hearts to believe on his dear son; the word that is translated ordained, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it signifieth chosen, appointed, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained; some would translate the words, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as were fitted and disposed in themselves for eternal life, believed; but what an absurd things is this? for then it would follow, that men were fitted for eternal life before they believed, when as Christ faith, He that believeth on the son, hath everlasting life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctrine</hi> 1. That the God of all Grace, whose counsel shall stand, and who will do all his pleasure out of meer Grace, hath absolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordained, chosen, and appointed a certain number of poor sinners unto eternal life and glory.</p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:119986:69"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. That though so many despise and slight Christ; yet those who are ordained, cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen, and appointed unto eternal life, shall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly believe through Grace; the Lord will give them Faith.</p>
            <p>We begin with the first of these Doctrines; for the opening of which, according to the measure of the gift of Christ we shall</p>
            <p n="1">I. Shew you how this ordaining and chosing unto eternal life is held forth in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Its held forth to be from all eternity; this choosing is not in time; we love him because he first loved us, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.4.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deus nihil cognoscit, vel vult, jam, quod etiam ah aeterno non noverit atque volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit.</hi> Piscators Theses. p. 309.</note>
               <hi>Who hath chosen us in him before the foundation of the world,</hi> that is to say, we who now believe in Christ, were chosen in him from all eternity; so <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11, 12, 13. Before the children were yet born, neither had done good or evil, that the purpose of God according to Election might stand, not of works, but of him that calleth, <hi>Jacob have I loved, and Esau have I hated;</hi> let not Christians think that God did not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain them to eternal life before they believed; O he loved you with a <hi>Jacob.</hi> love from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. <hi>before the world began;</hi> And saith <hi>Job</hi> concerning God, he is of one minde, and who can turn him? and, saith he, perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:119986:70"/>the thing that is appointed for me; God is not of one minde in time, and in another from eternity, but of one minde. (<hi>Job</hi> 23. 14.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Lords ordaining a certain number to eternal life, was not out of a foresight of their faith and good works, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.4. he chose us that we should be holy, not that he foresaw we of our selves would be more holy and better then others; but that we should be holy and without blame before him in love; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is no Doctrine that will make men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spair, as the Papists imagine, and the By-shops of iniquity in former times, who therefore forbad any to preach Election from all eternity; but I say its no Doctrine to make men despair; for though they at present be wicked and prophane yet seeing the Lord hath not elected any for any deserts in themselves, but hath loved them freely, they have no cause to despair that they belong not to the Election of Grace; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.5. saith the Apostle, <hi>Having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destinated us to the adoption of children by Iesus Christ according to the good pleasure of his will;</hi> I, thats the reason why the Lord hath ordained any of you to eternal life; not for any desert in you above others, but it was the fathers pleasure to give you a kingdom; the Lord was free either to ordain you to eternal life, or to damn you; but it was his pleasure, the good pleasure of his will; when the Lord from all eternity had all
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:119986:70"/>the sons of men in his eye, he had mercy upon whom he would have mercy, and ordered our eternal conditions according to the counsel of his own will.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God hath ordained Jesus Christ his dear son to be the way and means by which those whom he hath ordained to eternal life shall be saved, and by no other means; therefore a certain number are said in the Text to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained unto eternal life; so the Lord Jesus, the Apostle saith, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 20. was fore-ordained before the foundation of the world; hence in that place named before, we are said to be chosen in him who hath suffered for our sins, the just for the unjust, that he might bring us to God; he was ordained to bring us to that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, unto which we were ordained by the father; hence also doth the Apostle say <hi>the gift of God is eternal life through Iesus Christ our Lord, (Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>ult.</hi>) and saith he in another place, In hope of eternal life, which God that cannot lye promised before the world began, (<hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 19.) this eternal life was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to Christ as the head of that body the Church, for whom he was to die; and in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place saith he Who hath saved and called us, not according to our works, but according to his own purpose and grace, which was given us in Christ Jesus before the world began; and further, He hath not appointed us unto wrath,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:119986:71"/>but to obtain salvation by our Lord Jesus; that eternal life, that the Lord hath ordained or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed any of us to, he hath ordained and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed us to obtain by Jesus Christ; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Scripture telleth us how he <hi>hath laid help upon one that is mighty,</hi> and laid our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties upon Christ, and that by his stripes we are healed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Those who are thus ordained unto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, are through the blood of Christ which cleanseth them from all sin, as righteous before God as if they had never sinned; having all their sins forgiven them for his names sake, who hath born the chastisement of their peace; hence saith the Apostle, <hi>Who can lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect?</hi> that is, those whom he hath ordained unto eternal life; for saith he, Its God that justifieth; its Christ that hath died, yea rather that is risen again, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33, 34.) Though your sins are more then the hairs of your head, yet you are justified freely by Grace, through the redemption which is in Jesus Christ; the Law can lay nothing to your charge; for Christ is the end of the Law for righteousness; and hath taken away the curse of the Law by being made a curse for you.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Its impossible for the Elect and those that are ordained unto eternal life, to be totally and finally deceived in those things that are necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to salvation; but they are preserved to the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:119986:71"/>heavenly kingdom, unto which they were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, and are kept by the mighty power of God through Faith unto salvation, (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.) and therefore in that 24 of <hi>Matthew,</hi> Christ having told them <hi>v.</hi> 5. that many should come in his name, and say I am Christ, and deceive many, saith, <hi>v.</hi> 24. that the false Christs and false Prophets shall shew great signs and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, in so much that <hi>if it were possible, they should deceive even the very Elect;</hi> Mark, if it were possible; but as if Christ had said, though many shall be deceived by these false Prophets, and shall follow their pernicious ways, yet it is impossible for the Elect, those whom my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath ordained to eternal life, to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by them; for though the Elect may err in things of less concernment, yet the Spirit of Christ will lead them into all truth that is neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, that is essential to a Christian; and we have a notable Text to cleer this further, in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17, 18, 19. The Apostle having spoken of <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetas,</hi> how their words did eat as a Canker, and that had overthrown the Faith of some, perswading them that the Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection was past already; <hi>Nevertheless saith he the foundation of God standeth sure, having this seal, the Lord knoweth them that are his;</hi> as if the Apostle had said, <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetas</hi> may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive many, and may draw many Disciples after them; but the foundation of God standeth sure,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:119986:72"/>the Lord knoweth them that are his, he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth whom he hath chosen and ordained unto eternal life; and let <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetas,</hi> and all the devils in hell do what they can, they cannot pluck any of them out of his hands: all the policy of the devil, and all the wit of the greatest Scholars in the world cannot deceive the weakest Christian totally and finally in any point necessary to salvation.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Those whom the Lord hath ordained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternal life, he hath as well ordained them to the means as to the end; that is to say, To faith in the Lord Jesus, effectual calling and perseverance; hence the Apostle speaketh of our being <hi>called according to his purpose, Rom.</hi> 8.28. So that it was not onely the purpose of God to give us eternal life, but also it was his purpose also to give us faith in his son to call us out of darkness into marveilous light, and so to make us meet for the inheritance of the Saints in light, <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.3. I have loved thee with an everlasting love; therefore with my lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving-kindness have I drawn thee; no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n comes to Christ but he whom the Father draweth; and he draweth all those to Christ whom he hath thus loved with an everlasting love, and thus ordained unto eternal life; and therefore saith the Apostle, whom he hath predestinated, them he hath also called.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>All things shall work together for good to
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:119986:72"/>them that love God who are the called according to his purpose</hi> (<hi>Rom</hi> 8.28. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>ult.</hi>) all things, all their sufferings and afflictions, as the Apostle saith, Our light afflictions that are but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, work for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory; all their temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, poverty, sickness, disgrace in this world, all work together for their good; all their losses, crosses; that when they shall see another day how the Lord turned those evils to good, they shall see and say, they could not have been with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any of them; and though they dare not sin that Grace may abound, yet they see that their sins make them walk more humbly with God, make Christ more precious to them, and death it self worketh good to them; for thereby they come to that eternal life and glory, unto which the Lord hath chosen them, and ordained them, they come to that rest, for the people of God to stand before his face for ever.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Those whom the Lord hath ordained unto eternal life can never fall away, shall never be left, nor finally and totally forsaken of God; for he is the Father of lights, and with him there is no variableness, nor shadow of turning, (<hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17.) as he loved them from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, so he loveth them to all eternity; the gifts and calling of this unchangeable God, are without repentance, he changeth not: therefore we sons of <hi>Jacob,</hi> notwithstanding
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:119986:73"/>our many weaknesses and failings, are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed;
<note place="margin">Semelelectus, semper dile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus.</note> once chosen in Christ, we are always beloved; the Lord knew from all eternity, all the sins that ever we should commit; and yet he set his heart and love upon us, and ordained us unto eternal life, unto which all the Elect are as sure to be brought, as if they were there already: I know this doctrine is very much distasted by the world; and it was one of the Articles which the bloody Papists laid to that famous Martyr <hi>John Hus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Book of Martyrs <hi>pag.</hi> 226.</note> whom they put to death, That the predestinate cannot fal from grace; for they have a certain radical grace rooted in them, although they may be deprived of the abundance of Grace, and the vigour and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of Grace for a time; perseverance in Grace is the fruit of electing love; and whom the Lord hath ordained unto eternal life, he will give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them eternal life, and they shall never perish, neither any be able to pluck them out of his hands; they shall not totally and finally depart from him, and so perish, (<hi>Joh.</hi> 10.28. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.) but he will put his fear into their hearts, that they shall never depart from him; and all the devils in hell shall not be able to pull them out of the hands of the Father, who is greater then all, and holds them fast in the arms of free-grace, so that the gates of hell shall not prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them; so that this Mount-Sion, this cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:119986:73"/>generation shall not be moved, but are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served to the heavenly kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 1. This Doctrine, will some say, will make men licencious, and live as they list.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> The Lords absolute ordaining of a certain number to eternal life, can no way make any of them who are so ordained, to take liberty for sin; for all the chosen generation are led by the spirit of God, which is the Spirit of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and they know they were created in Christ Jesus unto good works, (<hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10.) which God before ordained they should walk in them; when the Lord ordained them to eternal life, he ordained them to holiness and good works, and did predestinate them, as to eternal life, so also to be conformable to the image of his son, that as they have born the image of the earthly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they may bear the image of the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and therefore all that are thus ordained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternal life, shall put on the new man, which after the image of God is created in righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and true holiness: and therefore Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from hell &amp; wrath, do not work so much upon this chosen generation, to keep them from sinning, but their being under the comforts, under the power and teachings of free-grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. But seeing all were lost in <hi>Adam,</hi> why did God ordain some to eternal life, and not all?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> He hath mercy upon whom he will have mercy; and I may answer with the Apostle,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:119986:74"/>
               <hi>Who art thou that repliest against God?</hi> shall the thing formed say to him that formed it, why hast thou made me thus? <hi>(Rom.</hi> 9.) Is there any unrighteousness with God? God forbid: we allow the sons of men to make choice of whom they will for their servants, and refuse others: and to make choice of whom they will for their friends, heirs; and yet vain man will scarce allow the great God of Heaven and earth liberty to choose whom he will for his servants, friends, heirs, and to refuse others: but he doth whatsoever he will, and giveth no account of his matters.</p>
            <p>The use that may be made of this Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Its of use to the Saints to keep them hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and to exclude boasting: O let him that glorieth, glory in the Lord. When a Saint shall consider, I was in the Lords hands, as clay in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e hand of the Potter: I was at his dispose to all eternity, whether I should be for ever sent to Hell, where is weeping, and wailing, and gnash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of teeth, or enjoy his presence for ever, where is fulness of joy: I was as sinful as any, as rebellious as any; the Lord saw no more worth in me then any other: and therefore, O what cause have I to lie low before him; I have not made my self to differ, nothing but his free love hath made a difference between me and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; it was not because I was more towardly then others in the day of grace: no, I was as a Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock unaccustomed to the yoak; only the Lord by
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:119986:74"/>an Almighty power of free-grace, turned me and I was turned, O the unsearchable riches of his Grace! as Christ said to his Disciples to keep them humble, ye have not chosen me, but I have chosen you; and may a believer say, though now I am made a partaker of the divine nature, and have Christ formed in me, and have much of God in me: yet the Lord loved me freely, even when I was in my blood and filthiness, and had no beauty in me; and all the graces that I have, are the comeliness which he hath put upon me; it was not my willing or running, but God that shewed mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋse</hi> 2. It may be of use to the Saints under weaknesses and corruptions, Lord thou knowest when thou ordainedst me unto eternal life, all the sins that ever I should commit; thou knewest how little glory thou shouldst have by me, and yet thou didst chose me to life and glory; O my God, thou hast loved me freely, and though I have so many weaknesses and failings, yet thou wilt not cast me off.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋse.</hi> 3. This Doctrine lets us see the freeness of Grace. O that when God had all the sons of men in his view, and saw them all in a lost and undone condition, that he should ordain this or that poor soul unto eternal life! O what ravish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, inamouring, astonishing grace was this! I believe its that which the Saints to all eternity shall admire and wonder at, saying, O that ever
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:119986:75"/>God should remember me in my low estate, and bring me unto this glory! What, ordain such a sinful creature as I am to eternal life, to stand before his face for ever, and be ever with the Lord? O that we could now see this chosing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love in the heights, and depths, and breadths, and lengths of it; it would appear wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to us, it would make us cry out, O that God who might justly have ordained me to hell, wrath, and eternal death, that ever he should ordain me to eternal life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋse.</hi> 4. This is matter of strong conlolation unto the Saints, as Christ said to his Disciples, Rejoyce that your names are written in the Book of life, (<hi>Luke</hi> 10.20.) One that hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted and experienc't the strong consolation that cometh from the knowledge of chosing love, would not for 10000 worlds be one of those that have no part nor interest in that choice; and however many slight this ordaining to eternal life from all eternity, and the Lords writing our names in the book of life from all eternity, as <hi>John, Mary, Thomas;</hi> yet the time is coming, when whoever is not found written in the book of life, shall be cast into the lake of fire, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.15. And for that holy City, the new <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> there shall in no wise enter into it any thing that defileth, neither whatsoever worketh abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, or maketh a lye, but they which are written in the Lambs book of life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27.</p>
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:119986:75"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋse.</hi> 5. You that know you are of this bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed number, O that you may walk answerable to the great love of God towards you, O how should this make you lay out your selves for God, and be willing to spend and be spent for him; O say, hath the Lord ordained me unto eternal life, and shall not I be willing if his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry call for it, be willing to part with this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral life for him? as the Martyr said, Welcome the Cross of Christ, welcome eternal life; and for holiness, you who are the chosen generation, and the royal Priesthood, (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.) you must be a peculiar people, you must deny all ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and worldly lusts, that you may shine as lights in the world, being holy and harmless, as sons of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋse.</hi> 6. If it be so that there are a certain number of poor sinners ordained to eternal life and glory; why then as the Apostle saith, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Give diligence to make your Calling and Election sure,</hi> that is to say, make sure that you are elected by your being called out of darkness into marvellous light; thus we know our Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; for whom he hath predestinated, saith the Apostle, them he hath also called; O how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are there here amongst us, that live without God in the world, and without Christ in the world! but if you belong to the number of the chosen generation, the Lord will call you into the fellowship of his son Jesus Christ.</p>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:119986:76"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaere.</hi> Why doth the Lord suffer some cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen vessels, such as <hi>Paul</hi> was to go on 20, 30, it may be 40 yeers sometimes before he call them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> 1. If I should give no other answer to this, then that the Lord suffereth them to go on in their natural condition thus for a great while, because it seemeth good in his sight, it were sufficient.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> 2. But secondly, the Lord hereby lets poor creatures see the freeness and fulness of grace.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The freeness of Grace, that the Lord should save and call poor sinners that went on many yeers in their ignorance, prophaness, sins and rebellions against him; and the freeness of Grace, that the Lord should call a sinner that hath been a rebel against him so long.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The fulness of Grace; Hence saith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possle <hi>Paul,</hi> I who was a blasphemer, an injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous person, I obtained mercy, and the Grace of God was exceeding abundant, (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13, 14) Mark, the Grace of God was not onely abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, but exceeding abundant; <hi>Paul</hi> was an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect vessel, and yet went on many yeers in his sins and rebellions against God; and now for God to call such a great sinner, here was Grace exceeding abundant; this sheweth a free Christ, and a full Christ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> 3. God hath appointed a certain time for the calling of those whom he hath ordained unto eternal life, which time and season will be
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:119986:76"/>most for the glory of his free love to them, and in that time they shall certainly be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for he that hath determined at such a time to call us, is able to do it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> 4. That others may have encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to come to Christ, such a one as <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> and many others, though they lived many years in a natural condition, yet were called, though at the ninth, tenth or eleventh hour: and Lord, I wait upon thee to call me; and speak Lord, for I desire to hear thy voice; and <hi>Paul</hi> saith, that Jesus Christ shewed forth all long-suffering in him for a pattern to them who should afterwards believe on him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life everlasting. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <p>Now to make an end of this first point, I still press home this exhortation, to make your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Election sure; O consider this day whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you be effectually called; hath the sound of the everlasting Gospel awakened you? have you heard the voice of the son of God? see 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.4, 5. Knowing brethren, Beloved, your Election of God, for our Gospel came not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in word onely, but also in power and in the Holy-Ghost, and in much assurance; this is an evidence of your Election of God, that he hath ordained you unto eternal life; when as the Gospel of Christ cometh in the power of the spirit of Christ into your hearts, that the preaching of the Gospel openeth the everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:119986:77"/>doors of your hearts for the Lord Jesus the King of Glory to enter in, and to dwell in your hearts by Faith; this I say is a certain evidence of your being ordained unto eternal life; but if our Gospel be hid, its hid to them that are lost.</p>
            <p>I know you cannot all believe and receive this Doctrine which I have preacht to you this day; but as Christ said, he that is able to receive it, let him receive it, &amp; lay up these sayings in his heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs.</hi> 2. THat though many despise and reject the Lord Jesus Christ; yet those whom the Lord hath ordained to eternal life, shall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly believe on Christ; the Lord will give them Faith.</p>
            <p>Methinks the naming of this Doctrine from the Text taketh away that passionate objection of some against Election of a certain number to life and glory from all eternity; their Objection is, If there be such an absolute ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of a certain number to eternal life, what need the Gospel be preach'd? they shall certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be saved. This Text furnisheth us with a full answer to it: for this is cleer from it, that those whom the Lord hath ordained to eternal life, that he hath also appointed them to believe on the Lord Jesus Christ; now the preaching of the Gospel is the ordinary way that God taketh to work Faith; or take it thus, The Lord hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen and ordained a certain number of poor
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:119986:77"/>creatures to eternal life; He hath appointed that these shall believe on the Lord Jesus Christ, and Faith cometh by hearing, as the Apostle saith, How shall they believe on him of whom they have not heard, and how shall they hear with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a preacher? <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Two considerations mightily establish the spirits of those that preach the Gospel.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That though many despise and reject the Lord Jesus Christ, yet as the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> said, Yet shall I be glorious in the eyes of the Lord; and saith he, My Judgement is with the Lord, and my work is with my God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That as many as are ordained to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, shall believe on Christ; for as it was here, so will it be unto the end of the world, that in every Family, Town, City, Nation, as many as are ordained to eternal life, the Lord will give them Faith; and although the precious word to many of you, is as water spilt upon the ground, and you profit no more then the seats you sit on; yet this beareth up my spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.7. The Election hath obtained, though the rest are blinded and hardned; and therefore saith Christ to the Pharises, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.25, 26. ye believe not because ye are not of my sheep; but saith he, My sheep hear my voice; and because they only believe on Christ, therefore true Faith is called the Faith of Gods Elect, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1.</p>
            <p>Now we come to shew you what it is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on Christ.</p>
            <pb n="140" facs="tcp:119986:78"/>
            <p>Its to receive the Lord Jesus Christ the King of Glory into our hearts, and to rest and relye upon him, and upon him onely; for life and for salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Explanation.</hi> Its to receive the Lord Jesus Christ] Thus Christ describeth Faith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.11, 12. To as many as received him, to them gave he power to become the sons of God, even to as many as believed on his Name: so that to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on his Name is to receive him; its not a receiving of this or that opinion or Notion of Christ, but there is in believing a receiving of Christ himself; the everlasting doors which were bolted and lockt against Christ, are set open, that he the King of Glory may come and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in; hence saith the Apostle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine your selves whether ye be in the Faith or no; know ye not your selves how that Iesus Christ is in you, except ye be rebrobates? there the Apostle maketh being in the Faith, and Iesus Christs being in us, all one.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Further, its a receiving of the Lord Iesus Christ, the King of Glory] At Conversion a soul receiveth Iesus Christ as a King, to rule, reign, and govern in him, desiring that Christ may subdue all things unto himself in the heart; and though other Lords have had dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him, yet now he desireth that all high thoughts and imaginations should be cast down, and the Lord Iesus Christ onely command and rule in him.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:119986:78"/>3. Further, its a receiving of the Lord Iesus Christ the King of glory into our hearts; many receive notions of Christ into their heads, and think they are some body, they can hold an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and can say, that Jesus Christ died for all <hi>Adams</hi> posterity, and so for them, and think they have attained a great matter; Alas, the bed is too short, this covering is too scant; O doth Jesus Christ live in your hearts! Is Christ in you the hope of glory! If Christ be not in you whilst you live, there is no hope of glory for you when you die; doth the Lord Jesus dwell in your hearts by Faith? as the Apostles phrase is, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. Can you say with the Apostle <hi>Paul,</hi> I live, yet not I, but Christ liveth in me; that you do not so much live and act, as Christ lives and acts in you, and that the life that you live in the flesh, is by the Faith of the son of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Further, its to rest, relie, and trust unto the Lord Jesus, and to him onely for salvation; not trusting to Christ and your works together; but looking upon our selves as the greatest of sinners, and all our own righteousness but men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struous rags, and so count all things but loss and dung, that we may win Christ, and be found in him, not having on us our own righteousness, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law, but that which is by the Faith of Christ, the righteousness which is of God by Faith, (<hi>Philip.</hi> 3.8, 9.) so that those who go about to establish their own righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:119986:79"/>believe not on Christ, submitting not to the righteousness which is of God by Faith; and yet these will needs be called Christians, like that <hi>Isai.</hi> 4.1. In that day seven women shall take hold of one man, saying, We will eat our own bread, and wear our own apparel, onely let us be called by thy name, to take away our reproach; so many would be named by Christs name, to take away their reproach; but they will eat their own bread, live upon their own righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness; and wear their own apparel; they will be found in their own righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; but these are not the Spouses of Iesus Christ, these are not true believers; there must be an uncloathing and stripping of our selves naked, that we may be cloathed upon with the Robes of Christs righteousness; a true believer is nothing in himself, and all in Christ. Now of this Faith there are several degrees.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Little Faith, as Christ said to his Disciples, <hi>O ye of little Faith;</hi> indeed it may be said to most of us that are Christians, O ye of little Faith, and little love, and little strength; we are but as the smoaking flax, and as the bruised Reed (<hi>Rom.</hi> 4.19.) yet if our Faith be true, though it be little, our condition is safe; for he with whom we have to do will not quench the smoaking flax, nor break the bruised Reed; a little Faith is better then ten thousand worlds: such Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans lie under many doubtings, and often go
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:119986:79"/>mourning without the Son; and when at the best, cry out, Lord I believe, help my unbelief; and though such have not so much comfort as others, yet their condition is as safe; Iesus Christ saith, He that believeth on the Son, hath ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting life, (<hi>Joh.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi>) He doth not say, he one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that knoweth, he that believeth and hath a strong Faith, hath eternal life; but he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth; thou that hast true Faith in the Lord Iesus, though it be little, thou art as sure of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, as <hi>Paul,</hi> or the highest scholars in the school of Christ, though thou dost not know it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Great Faith, as Christ said to the woman, O woman, great is thy Faith; we are said to have great Faith, when we are able not to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion the love of God towards us in afflictions, temptations, chastisements; yea in our slips and backslidings, (<hi>Luk.</hi> 7.9.) that even then, though we abhor our selves in dust and ashes for our backslidings, that yet we question not the love of God to us, this sheweth us to have great Faith, and strong Faith.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Degree of Faith is, when a soul attaineth to that which the Scripture calleth full assurance of Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. A soul that hath attained to this degree of Faith, is more holy then other Christians, more dead to the world, and seldom is troubled with doubtings; all Christians are to press after this; the Lord sometimes gives the Saints this full assurance of Faith, when they
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:119986:80"/>are to walk in the valley of the shadow of death and this maketh them fear no evil, but fortifieth their hearts against death, which is the King of terrours; O how welcome and easie is death to such! they are desirous to be dissolved to be with Christ.</p>
            <p>I would speak something further to you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Faith.</p>
            <p>As first, That it is the gift of God, its not a thing in our own power; if without Christ we can do nothing, then not believe on Christ; men talk great swelling words of the power of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but what saith the Scripture, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.19, 20. and what is the exceeding greatness of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to us ward who do believe according to the working of his mighty power, which he wrought in Christ when he raised him from the dead; you that have had true Faith wrought in you, you know there was mighty power put forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; that false vain Faith which many have, is wrought without this mighty power; but saith the Scripture, They shall be a willing people in the day of my power, (<hi>Psal.</hi> 110.3.) When the day of Christs power cometh, then we are made of unwilling, willing to come to Christ; and saith the Lord, I have loved thee with an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting love, therefore with my loving kindness have I drawn thee, (<hi>Ier.</hi> 31.3.) as if he had said, Thou wast backward, and stubborn, unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the day of Grace, but I had infinite un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:119986:80"/>love to thee, and therefore with my lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindness have I drawn thee, as a dead man, call him, yet he stirreth not, he cometh not to you, we are naturally dead in trespasses and sins; but a dead man may be drawn whither you will; the Lord cometh, and with his Almighty power plucks us, and draweth us as firebrands out of the fire; Faith therefore is called the work of God, not onely because its the work that is most pleasing, without which its impossible to please God; but likewise because it is of his working in us, and therefore called Faith of the operation of God, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. Its as hard a thing for us to believe the Gospel as to keep the Law.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Those to whom the Lord hath given true Faith, its impossible for them totally and finally to lose that Faith; for as Jesus Christ is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, so is he the finisher of our Faith, (<hi>Heb.</hi> 12 2.) perfecting that which concerneth us. Jesus Christ payed for <hi>Peter,</hi> that his Faith might not fail, <hi>Luke</hi> 22, 32. and the father alwayes hears him; and for this cause they can never come to be unbelievers again; and indeed Faith is kept as a spark in the midst of the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. O what a wonder is it, that notwithstanding all the sins and backslidings of Saints; that yet all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils in Hell cannot make us let go our hold on Christ, but they will say in dark days and sad hours, as <hi>Job</hi> did, <hi>though he kill me, yet will I
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:119986:81"/>put my trust in him,</hi> thus we are kept by the mighty power of God, thorow Faith, unto sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, that the Lord keeps them in a way of believing and dependance upon Christ. He that hath begun a good work in them, will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it to the day of Christ, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.6.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Faith is given to us upon Christs account and for his sake; as <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.29. its given to you on the behalf of Christ to believe; its that which Jesus Christ hath purchased for all those for whom he died, as well as remission and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveness of sins.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Faith its an excellent Grace; some call it the mother Grace; our joy and peace com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in by believing, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 15.13.) we draw waters out of the wells of salvation with the Bucket of Faith; by faith also we have access to God with a holy boldness; we come to him, (<hi>Eph.</hi> 3.12) as a child to his Father, yea we live by the Faith of the son of God; yea, we do wonderful things by faith, as we read in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. of those who through faith subdued king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, wrought righteousness, out of weakness were made strong, by faith we obey God and follow his leadings in straights, difficulties, and hard things to flesh and blood, as we read in that chapter, how <hi>Abraham</hi> by faith, when he was called out by the Lord from his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and acquaintance, obeyed and went out, not knowing whither he went; yea by faith we
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:119986:81"/>honour God as much, if not more, then by our Prayers and other performances; as it was said, <hi>Abraham</hi> believed and gave glory to God. And the reason why God honoureth Faith so much, is because faith honoureth him so much.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋse</hi> 1. Is it so that as many as are ordained unto eternal life, though others reject Christ, yet they believe on him unto life everlasting? then O examine whether you believe on Christ, prove your selves whether you be in the faith or no.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Faith of Gods elect worketh by love,</hi> Gal. 5.6. Its no notional thing, but it worketh in the heart dear love and affections unto Christ; can a man believe on Christ, and yet have no love to Christ? it worketh also love in our hearts unto all Saints, as the Apostle, <hi>Philem.</hi> 5. puts them together, Faith in the Lord Jesus, and love unto all Saints; yea and this faith is said to work by love, because those who truly believe on Christ are not put upon good works, by le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal terrors and feare of hell, but the love of Christ constraineth them to holiness, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strains them from sin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To them who truely <hi>believe, Jesus Christ is precious,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.7. Men may have a not onal knowledge of Jesus Christ, and say with the Spouse, that he is the chiefest of ten thousand, and that he is altogether lovely; but yet still Christ is not precious to them; its but those that have an experimental knowledge of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:119986:82"/>of Christ, they have precious thoughts of Christ; therefore saith <hi>David, Thou art fairer then the children of men; Grace is poured into thy lips.</hi> O consider, Is Jesus Christ precious to you? is he the Pearl of great price in your eye? sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you cannot lay the whole weight of your souls upon Christ, but you must have precious thoughts of him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. True faith is lively and active in holiness; therefore the Apostle saith that faith without works is dead (<hi>Jam.</hi> 2.20.) True Faith quickens us to holiness and walking with God, and doth not make us loose and licencious, but it purifieth the heart and life, (<hi>Act.</hi> 15.9.) The more we believe on Christ, the more abounding in good works; the more we believe on Christ, the more power against temptation, and the more power against corruption.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋse.</hi> 2. To you that believe on Christ; let me beseech you to be careful to maintain good works, as <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.8. This is a faithful saying, and these things I will that thou affirm constantly, that they which have believed in God might be careful to maintain good works; these things are good and profitable unto men. Mark, The Apostle would have Believers be constantly put upon good works, yet not as to think to be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by them in whole or in part; that is freely by grace; but saith he, these things are profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto men; to live convincing lives, to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:119986:82"/>and harmless, as sons of God, doth adorn the Doctrine of God our Saviour, doth also convince men that God is in us of a truth. O how careful should believers be in their walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings! how circumspect! the Apostle biddeth them <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.1. that whatsoever things are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, just, lovely, of good report, and if there be any vertue, and if there be any praise, think on those things: I pray observe that Scripture; believers must not onely be careful that they do nothing but what is honest and just; to say such a thing is just for me to do; but what followeth? whatsoever things are lovely and of good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; so that a believer must consider further, will such an action present Religion lovely in the eyes of those that are without? is such a thing of good report? will it not cause the way of truth to be ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l spoken of? O we should ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deny our selves in many things, which it may be we might do lawfully, then that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on should suffer by us, and the Doctrine of God and our Saviour be blasphemed. In a word, a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever in his walkings should not consider onely whether it be lawful for him to do this or that, but also whether it be expedient.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let me speak a word to them that believe, that ye may believe as the Apostle saith, 1 <hi>Ioh</hi> 5.15. <hi>These things have I written unto you that believe on the name of the Son of God, that ye may know that ye have eternal life, and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:119986:83"/>that ye may believe on the name of the son of God;</hi> that is to say, that their faith might be stronger; and the Apostle writing to the Believers, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.3. saith he, we are bound to thank God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways for you, as it is meet, because your faith groweth exceedingly. O tis an excellent thing when faith groweth exceedingly; when little faith groweth great faith, and weak faith strong faith; Now those things by which our faith groweth are.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By our union with Christ; as the branches of a tree grow by their union with the tree, and fetching sap from the root, so doth our faith grow by union with Christ, partaking of the sap and fatness of the Lord Jesus that green fir-tree in whom is all our fruit found.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our faith groweth by afflictions, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutions; its with the faith of the Saints as with Camomile; the more its trodden upon, the more it groweth; and saith the Lord by the Prophet, I will leave a poor and an afflicted people, and they shall trust in the name of the Lord; when the people of God are an afflicted people, then doth their faith and dependance upon God grow strong, and as Mount-Sion which cannot be moved; and therefore some Christians have found this by experience, that when they have gone on in a prosperous condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the world, they have not had so much faith and dependance upon God, as he hath been
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:119986:83"/>pleased to give them in straights and difficulties.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Our faith groweth by promises; they are indeed but dry breasts when the Lord doth not speak to us by them; but the Lord giving in such a promise to the soul, as <hi>Hos.</hi> 14.4. <hi>I will heal thy backslidings, I will love thee freely:</hi> O how doth it encrease our faith, and strengthen our faith, and as faith at first conversion in Gods ordinary way of dispensation cometh by hearing! so 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2 2. <hi>As new born babes desire the sincere milk of the word, that ye may grow thereby,</hi> and likewise Eph. 4. <hi>He hath given gifts unto men, for the perfecting till we all come to the unity of the faith and of the knowledge of the son of God unto perfect men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Praying in the Holy-Ghost is a means of the growth and increase of faith <hi>Jude</hi> 20. Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up your selves in your most holy faith, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Holy-Ghost; therefore, O that you who are believers, might pray much in the Holy-Ghost, saying with the Disciples; <hi>Lord, increase our Faith;</hi> our Faith is but little Faith; Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease it; O give us the full assurance of Faith.</p>
            <p>O that thus you might grow in Faith; where faith groweth and increaseth, there holiness in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaseth, love to Jesus Christ increaseth, true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance increaseth, as a man of God saith, All the tears of true repentance come trickling down from the eye of faith. Thus if you grow in the grace of faith, you will also grow in the grace of love, and you will grow in the grace
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:119986:84"/>of Repentance, self-denial, patience and every good work.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋse</hi> 4. A word to you who are unbelievers. O that you may believe on the Lord Jesus Christ that you may be saved! he that believeth not on the Lord Jesus, the wrath of God abideth on him. O you little think what it is to lie under the wrath of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. But its presumption for me to believe; I am not humbled enough to believe; I must tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry till I be so and so qualified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> Jesus Christ faith, whosoever cometh to him, he will in no wife cast our, (<hi>Joh.</hi> 6.) and saith by the Prophet, <hi>Ho every one that thirsteth, come ye to the waters, buy wine and milk without mony and without price,</hi> (<hi>Isa.</hi> 55.1.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. But I am a great sinner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> But Jesus Christ is a great Saviour, mighty to save; Christ is as mighty to save as sin is to damn; his blood cleanseth from all sin; (1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7.) and whosoever believeth on him shall be justified from all things, from which they cannot be justified by the Law of <hi>Moses;</hi> he is able to save to the utmost all them that come to God by him; and is not here encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment enough for the worst of sinners to come to Christ? there are some who think they doe much when they tell men that Jesus Christ died for all <hi>Adams</hi> posterity, and think that this will make men believe on Christ: I cannot but
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:119986:84"/>wonder that men should make that the subject of all their preaching, to perswade men that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ died for every one of them. Alas, go into a Town, and talk with men and women, and you shall scarce finde a man or woman that doth not believe that, unless it be two or three Christians in the Town; but the rest are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and prophane that which they believe; and its that which maketh them think their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is good; for they will say God is merciful, and Jesus Christ died for me, and for all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as their old Catechism taught them; what is this but to nourish men in their ignorance of Christ, giving them a broken reed to lean upon? but I say, is not here encouragement enough for sinners to come to Christ, that he is able to save to the utmost, and casts out none that come to him, but the arms of love and free grace em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them! O you that are most rebellious and sinful, come to Christ, you shall be welcom to him; though thou art sinful, yet Jesus Christ is righteous; though thou hast sinned, yet he hath suffered; believe on him, and thou shalt escape the damnation of hell, and there will be no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to you; and Jesus Christ doth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accept of those who are less sinners, when they come to him, but he accepts of <hi>Matthew</hi> a Publican, <hi>Paul</hi> a Blasphemer, <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> a harlot; O therefore that the Lord would put into your hearts this day to come to Christ; O, he will in no wise cast you out.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="154" facs="tcp:119986:85"/>
            <head>CHRISTS COMPASSIONS TO SINNERS.</head>
            <head type="sub">Sermon. III.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 10.33, 34.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>But a certain Samaritan as he journied came where he was, and whem he saw him, he had compassion on him: And went to him and bound up his wounds, pouring in oile and wine, and set him upon his own beast, and brought him to an Inne, and took care of him.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>OUr Lord Jesus Christ doth notably set forth in this Scripture, his great kindness and love to sinners, under the notion of a good <hi>Samaritan,</hi> and a man that fell among theeves;
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:119986:85"/>to some places of Scriptures Allegories are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, to some useful and convenient; as that parable of the seed, and the sower, and the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ground, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. and <hi>Paul</hi> speaking of <hi>Abrahams</hi> two sons, the one by a bondwoman, the other by a free woman, which things saith he, are an Allegory; for these are the two Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.22, 23, 24.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding, we must draw nothing by way of Allegory, but what is agreeable to other Scriptures which are more plain and more easily to be understood, <hi>ver.</hi> 30. <hi>A certain man went down from Jerusalem to Iericho</hi>] this cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain man may be <hi>Adam,</hi> the first man <hi>Adam,</hi> who went down from <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> from that state of holiness and communion with God, and fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thieves; these thieves are the devils which are the faln Angels, which stript off his rayment; <hi>Adam</hi> by his fall was stript of his rayment, 1. Outward, which was his innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that we read in <hi>Genesis</hi> that he saw his naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and was ashamed and hid himself. 2. They were stript of their spiritual rayment, that their souls were left naked; and its conceived by some that it was Christ that appeared to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve, Gen.</hi> 3.21. where it is said, Unto <hi>Adam</hi> and to his wife did the Lord God make coates of skins, and cloathed them; there he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion of them; and their being cloathed with coats of skins, might hold forth their being
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:119986:86"/>cloathed with Christs Righteousness; &amp; here was a notable discovery of the mercy and compassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this good Samaritan the Lord Jesus, that he should save <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> who brought themselves and all their posterity into a state of enmity and rebellion against God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And wounded him]</hi> O what a wound had <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> by his fall! such a wound, that unless this good Samaritan the Lord lesus heal him, he will die and perish; a wound which himself could never cure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And departed]</hi> So did the devil from <hi>Adam,</hi> when he had done him this mischief; left him in that miserable lost condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Half dead]</hi> There is a twofold life, spiritual and natural; he was half dead; spiritually dead, though he had a natural life; and so are all the sons of men by nature half dead; though they have a natural life, yet are they spiritually dead. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1. <hi>And you hath he quickened who were dead in trespasses and sins;</hi> and the Prodigals fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther saith, My son was dead and is alive, was lost and is found. The dead shall hear the voice of the son of man, and they that hear shall live.</p>
            <p>Vers. 31. <hi>There came a Priest that way, and when he saw him, be passed by on the other side; and likewise a Levite when he saw him, passed by on the other side]</hi> This holds forth the insufficiency of the Law to help us in our lost condition; the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:119986:86"/>Law made nothing perfect, but the bringing in of a better Hope did; <hi>(Heb.</hi> 6.19) by the which we draw nigh unto God; therefore the Lord Christ is said to have obtained a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Ministry, by how much also he is a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator of a better Covenant; established upon better Promises; for if that Covenant had been faultless, then should no place have been sought for the second; the Priest and Levite pass by and help him not; but saith the Text, A certain Samaritan as he came that way, when he saw him, had compassion on him, and went to him, and bound up his wounds, and poured in oyle and wine into his wounds. The Priests and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites of the Law leave him in his misery, weltring in his blood, but our pitiful and merciful High-Priest, the Lord Iesus, he hath compassion on him: this Samaritan in the Text, is the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ; the Thiefe is the devil, who is the cruellest, bloodiest Thief that ever was in the world; he is a Thiefe, because he seeketh to rob God of his glory, and seeketh to rob us of our precious soules; Thieves have many cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning tricks to bring about their purposes; so hath the devil; therefore in the Scripture we read that he hath devices, that he hath wiles, and that he is a cunning Serpent.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Doctrine.</head>
               <p>That Iesus Christ is the good Samaritane, who when all other things fail and help us not; yet
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:119986:87"/>he helps, seeketh and saveth poor lost ones; you see that the Priest and Levite help not; all things are but as Brooks that fail in Summer, but Iesus Christ that Fountain of living waters. <hi>David</hi> was in a sad condition, in <hi>Psal.</hi> 38.4, 5, 6, 7, 8. saith he, <hi>Mine iniquities are gone over my head, and are become a burden too heavy for me to bear; I am troubled, and go mourning all the day long; I have roared by reason of the disqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etness of my heart,</hi> And v. 11. saith he, <hi>My lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and my friends stand aloofe from my sore, and my kinsmen stand afar off.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus it is with us; the Law cannot help us, the devil seeketh to devour us, our own Consciences condemn us, and our friends and relations, like the Priest and Levite, stand aloof from our sores and wounds; and but that Iesus Christ the good Samaritan comes in to our help, we should perish; therefore saith <hi>David</hi> in the same Psalm, the 15. <hi>ver. In thee O Lord do I hope, thou wilt hear O Lord my God;</hi> he will, and help, and save; other things stand at a distance: yes, I have observed this, that men who have made it their business to dispute some controversies, and have had many dearly beloved notions and conceptions about them; yet in time of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and desertion those notions stand afar off and yeild no comfortings and revivings to the drooping fainting heart; nothing then but an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimental knowledge of, and true faith in the Lord Iesus stands the soul in stead.</p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:119986:87"/>
               <p>But that you may see more cleerly and fully, the tender mercies and compassions of this good Samaritan the Lord Iesus to poor lost ones, we shall make some exposition of the Text.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Shew you how Christ is said to journey.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How he hath Compassion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. How he went to him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. How he bound up his wounds.</p>
               <p n="5">5. What is meant by pouring in oyl into his wounds.</p>
               <p n="6">6. What is meant by pouring in wine into his wounds.</p>
               <p n="7">7. What is meant by setting of him upon his own beast.</p>
               <p n="8">8. What is meant by the Inn he brought him to.</p>
               <p n="9">9. How he took care of him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. How the Lord Iesus this good Samaritan is said to journey.</p>
               <p>By this is meant Christs being made flesh, and dweling amongst his; he took a journey from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to earth, to seek and to save that which was lost; he who was brought up always with God, and was continually his delight, came from the bosom of the Father, to bring us to the bosom of the Father.</p>
               <p>Things to be considered in Christs journey,</p>
               <p n="1">1. In what manner, form, and habit he came in; the Scripture tells us, he came in the form of a servant, though he was Lord of all, and the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:119986:88"/>brightness of the Fathers glory; yet in this journey he cometh in the form of a servant; (<hi>Philip.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8.) he came to do the will of him that sent him; the Lord Jesus came this journey in such a mean habit, that the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> saith, His visage was marred more then any of the sons of men; and that when men see him they shall see no beauty in him wherefore they should desire him; that is to say, those who looked onely at the outward appearance, seeing he came in the form of a servant, without any worldly pompe and state, therefore they would despise and reject him: but though the Lord Jesus came this first journey into the world in the form of a servant: yet the second journey, that ere long he will take from Heaven into this world, will be mighty and glorious, when he shall come and reign in Mount Sion, and before his Antients glorious, taking to him his great power; wherefore saith the Prophet <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saiab,</hi> Who is this that cometh from <hi>Edom</hi> with dyed garments of <hi>Bozrah,</hi> travailing in the greatness of his strength? (<hi>Isa.</hi> 63.1.) the Lord Jesus shall take that journey in the greatness of his strength coming in glory and Majesty; for then will the day of vengeance be in his heart, and the year of his redeemed be come.</p>
               <p>The second thing to be considered in Christs journey, is what accommodations he had; he saith himself, <hi>The Foxes have holes, and the Birds
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:119986:88"/>of the ayr have nests, but the son of man hath not whereon to lay his head,</hi> O the infinite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>discension of the fellow of the Lord of Hosts, that though he was rich, yet for our sakes he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came poor, that we through his poverty might be made rich.</p>
               <p>The third thing to be considered in Christs journey, is what usage he had from the world, when he journeyed and went up and down the world doing good; we finde that the <hi>Gadarens</hi> despised him, were weary of his company, and beseecht him to depart out of their coasts. How was he reproached, called <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> the Prince of Devils? all the while he was in the world, he was a man of sorrows, acquainted with grief, and we hid as it were our faces from him, and at last he was betrayed into the hands of sinners, and they crucified the Lord of Glory: thus he died, that we might live; and suffered for our sins, the just for the unjust, that he might bring us to God, offering up himself in the eternal spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that he might obtain an eternal Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for us; and being thus put to death in the flesh, it being impossible for this holy one to see corruption, he arose from the dead, and went to appear in the presence of God for us, and so the Heavens contain him until the time of the restitution of all things, when he will take ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther journey into this world in power and great glory, and then shall have dominion from
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:119986:89"/>Sea to Sea, from the Rivers to the ends of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e earth; Behold he cometh this journey ere long, <hi>Amen, even so come Lord Jesus, come quickly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The second thing, <hi>He had compassion on him;</hi> There is a notable Scripture to shew the Lords compassions to sinners, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.5, 6, 8. No eye pittied thee to doany of these unto thee, to have compassion on thee; as here, neither Priest nor Levite pittied thee, poor creature, to do any of these things unto him, to have compassion on him, to binde up his wounds, but saith the Lord there, When I passed by thee, and saw thee pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted in thy blood, I said unto thee, when thou wast in thy blood, live: O Christs compassions to sinners! he is eyes to the blinde, and feet to the lame: He standeth at the door and knocks, and saith, Open to me, He succoureth them that are tempted, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.18. we read of him, that in the days of his flesh he had compassion on the multitudes, and healed their sick; and the more bowels of mercy, and pitty, and compassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we have to them who are in the gall of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terness, the more like to this good Samaritan, the Lord Jesus.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>He went to him,</hi> Christ cometh to us before we come to him, we are drowning in the Sea of sin, and the Lord Jesus cometh to us, and taketh us by the hand, and lifts us out, puls us out, He went to the poor creature: we are dead in trespasses and sins, and Christ cometh to
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:119986:89"/>us, cometh to our graves, and saith, Awake from the dead: we are prisoners and cannot stir, are fettered with sin, but the Lord Jesus cometh and saith to the prisoners. Go forth, and to them that are in darkness, shew your selves. O a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hearted Christ, who is found of them that sought him not! this man did not seek the good Samaritan, but the good Samaritan sought him; Christ came to seek, as well as to save that which was lost, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.77, 78. The day-spring from on high hath visited us, to give light to them that sat in darkness; the day-spring from on high, is the Lord Jesus: and mark, he hath visited us, we were sick, and lay weltring in our blood: we stir not, but this good Samaritan cometh and visits the poor soul: and see further, To give light to them that sat in darkness: This was our condition, we sat in darkness, we did not set one step towards Christ, but sat still in our darkness of ignorance and sin, till Christ comes and guides our feet into the way of peace.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>He bound up his wounds,</hi> Christ cometh not in vain to poor souls, he cometh to do them good, to save them, comfort them, binde up their wounds, <hi>Isa.</hi> 61.1. The spirit of the Lord God is upon me, saith Christ, he hath annointed me to preach deliverance to the captives, and to binde up the broken hearted: My brethren, if you were wounded for sin, the tidings of this good Samaritan would be glad tidings to your
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:119986:90"/>souls: but O consider, when you have wounds of Conscience, doth this good Samaritan binde up your wounds, or do not ye your selves binde up your wounds with the rags of your own righteousness? And I pray observe, He bound up his wounds, not one wound onely, we have many wounds, many sores; now Christ binds up all the wounds, he maketh all right in the soul: Christ is a cure for all our wounds, and we may try this and the other, but we shall finde them all Physitians of no value, we shall have cure onely from the Lord Iesus; if the Priest and the Levite had come to the poor man, they could not have cured him, but the good Samaritan doth it throughly.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>He poured in oyl,</hi> What is meant by this?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Oyl holdeth forth the Spirit, the unction from the holy one. <hi>Psal.</hi> 41.7. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.20. This sheweth us how the Lord Iesus at conversion gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth poor creatures his Spirit; we have received, saith the Apostle, the Spirit, whereby we know the things that are freely given unto us of God, and it holdeth forth the graces of the Spirit, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.4. The wise virgins which are true Believers, they are said to have oyl in their Lamps, that is, the graces of the Spirit; so that Christs pouring in oyl, holds forth our receiving of his fulness, and Grace for Grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The oyl holdeth forth comfort and joy, Christ giveth the poor the oyl of joy for the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:119986:90"/>spirit of heaviness, <hi>Isa.</hi> 61.2, 3. and so, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the soul was without comfort, despairing, fainting, drooping, he comforts and cheareth up the soul: O poor Saints! Before this good Samaritan came and poured in this oyl, you were in a sad condition, but did not he bring comfort to your souls? Oyl maketh the face to shine, saith <hi>David, Psal.</hi> 104.15. Christ took up into the Mount in communion with them, and then as <hi>Moses,</hi> your faces did shine</p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>Andwine.</hi> The good Samaritan poureth in wine, not Vineger: what doth that hold forth? why the manifestation of Christs love to the soul; and as the Spouse saith, Thy love is better then Wine, <hi>(Cant.</hi> 1.2.) more chearing, comforting, warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; wine maketh glad the heart of man, <hi>Psal.</hi> 104.15. So doth the love of Christ: what is so welcom to a poor soul, as the manifestation of Christs love, the kisses of his mouth? Till Christ manifest his love, it is sad and heavy: now saith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Give wine to him that is of an heavy heart, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.6. O what a heavy heart hath a poor creature that is convinc't of sin by the spirit, till Christ come and manifest his love! O have none of you had heavy troubled hearts yet! If you have heavy hearts, Christs love and nothing else will refresh you.</p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>He set him on his own beast,</hi> This holdeth forth Christs bearing our sins in his own body upon the tree, bearing the chastisements of our
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:119986:91"/>peace, <hi>Isa.</hi> 53.5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. and so in that parable of the lost sheep, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.5. saith Christ, when he hath found the lost sheep, he layeth it on his shoulders rejoycing.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>He brought him to an Inn,</hi> This Inn is the Gospel, the Covenant of free grace; in this Inn every one that thirsteth, may buy wine and milk without money, and without price, <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.1.</p>
               <p n="1">1. An Inn is a place free for all comers: so is Christ and the Gospel, whosoever cometh to me, I will in no wise cast our, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.16. who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will, let him come and take of the water of life freely.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In an Inn you may have what you will call for: so here, whatsoever you ask in my Name, saith Christ, you shall receive it: yea the Lord saith, Before ye call I will answer, and whilst you are yet speaking I will hear: open thy mouth wide and I will fill it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You may be free in an Inn, and so you are in Christ; if the son shall set us free, then we shall be free indeed; the Gospel is the Royal Law of Liberty: and the Hosts that you read of, <hi>verse.</hi> 35. are the Ministers of the Gospel: to them Christ giveth two pence, that is, the Word and the Seals: this the good Samaritan provides for the poor converted sinner, the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere milk of the Word, that he may grow thereby: he hath given gifts to men for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of the Saints.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:119986:91"/>9. <hi>And took care of him;</hi> Christ took care of the poor creature, Christ is the head of the Church, and the head is the seat of care; what a care had Christ of <hi>Peter,</hi> Sathan desireth to winnow thee as Wheat, but I have prayed for thee that thy Faith fail not; Nay, ye shall see, <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.8. That Christ had more care of his Disciples, then he had of himself; saith he, I am he whom ye seek, take me, and let them go; Christ knew his Disciples had but little Faith, but saith he, Let them go: he never saith, let me go: What would become of the little childe, if the mother had not a care of it? it would fall into the fire, be in a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred mischiefs, and what would become of us, if Christ had not a care of us?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Christ taketh care that our wounds be healed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Christ taketh care that we do not fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thieves again.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Christ taketh care to keep us in the Inn of the Gospel, and maketh much of us, then carrieth us into his Wine-sellar, and his banner over us is love.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He taketh care that Satan shall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour us: had not Christ a care of us, what would Satan do to us?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Ʋse.</head>
               <p>Of comfort to sinners, here is a good Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan, the Lord Jesus, that can cure all your
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:119986:92"/>wounds: It was a saying of <hi>Luther,</hi> that Christ was an Hospital for wounded sinners; indeed the whole need not the Physitian: those who are whole, who have licked themselves whole by their own duties and good works, they see no need of this Physitian; but O you that see, that from the crown of the head to the sole of the foot, nothing but wounds and putrifying sores, take Christ for your Physitian; let this good Samaritan come and pour in oyl and wine into your wounds: if that you go to the Law for cure, you will be like the woman that had the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Issue thirty eight yeers, and could get no cure; but she cometh to Christ, and doth but touch the hem of his garment, and she was made whole; look unto him, he is the Brazen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, look unto him and be saved, all ye ends of the earth; whatsoever your wounds are, Christ can cure them; look out to no other for cure, neither to the Law, nor your selves; do not think to cure them your selves: but, O that this good Samaritan may come and binde up my wounds and pour in wine and oyl, that he may come and speak a word of comfort; create the fruit of the lips Peace, Peace.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>